<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons 1. The good fight. Preached at the funerall of Henry Sommaster of Pens-ford in the country of Deuon, Esquire. Ian. 1606. 2. The worth of the water of life. 3. Dauids longing, and Dauids loue. By Sam. Hieron.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116031</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851248</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851248</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03308)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1106:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons 1. The good fight. Preached at the funerall of Henry Sommaster of Pens-ford in the country of Deuon, Esquire. Ian. 1606. 2. The worth of the water of life. 3. Dauids longing, and Dauids loue. By Sam. Hieron.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The second sermon. The worth of the water of life" and "The third sermon. Dauids longing, and Dauids loue" with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sommaster, Henry, d. 1606 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16518:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Three SERMONS.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The good Fight. <hi>Preached at the Funerall of Henry</hi> Sommaſter of PENS-FORD in the County <hi>of Deuon, Eſquire. Ian.</hi> 1606.</item>
               <item>2. The worth of the water of Life.</item>
               <item>3. Dauids Longing, and Dauids Loue.</item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Greg. in Ezech. Hom. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Preacher ſhould be like the Smiths burning Iron, which not onely heateth thoſe that are neere, but caſteth ſparkes farre off.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By SAM. HIERON.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>HINC · LVCEM · ET · POCVLA · SACRA</head>
               <p>ALMA MATER CANTA BRIGIA</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT CAMBRIDGE Printed by IOHN LEGATE. <hi>Anno</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16518:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16518:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>To the right Worſhipful, Sir WILLIAM STRODE <hi>of Newing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the Countie of Deuon. Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, what, and how great my debt is to your Worſhip, it is very meet for me to remember, though it be not neceſſarie to acquaint the world with parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. My deſire hath bene, and is, to giue ſome teſtimonie of thankefulneſſe. Rich preſents, ſuch as in this crauing and catching age, do (as the Wiſeman ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 18.16.</note> 
               <hi>Enlarge a man, and leade him before great men,</hi> as you need not, ſo (I know) you expect not: ſure I am, I for my part am very vnable to beſtow. But (as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaid to the cripple at the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gate,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Such as</hi> I <hi>haue</hi> I <hi>giue,</hi> euen a few blotted leaues; ſuch perhaps, as in this <hi>itching-eared</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.</note> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, (wherin the moſt do more affect toyes then truth, and a flouriſh of words, rather then ſubſtance of matter) few will take notice of: yet ſuch as I doubt not but you, out of your loue to me, but chiefly out of your affection to Gods holy truth, will vouchſafe kindly to accept. For me, to commend (as deceitfull huckſters do their wares) either to you or to others, that which I here make tender of, were to proclaime
<pb facs="tcp:16518:3"/> to the world mine owne vanitie. <hi>Let another man praiſe thee, and not thine ovvne mouth,</hi> ſaith the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: <note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 27.2.</note> neither yet will I any way diſparage it: for that might be thought a ſecret begging of commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſubmit it to triall, if either to your ſelfe, or to any other of the <hi>Iſrael of God,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> it ſhall bring any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle encreaſe, either of ſound knowledge, or ſweet fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>in the myſtery of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 3.4.</note> I haue my reward, and ſhall thinke my labour well beſtowed. And ſo heartily, wiſhing the true good vnto your Worſhip, your good Ladie, your whole line and family, I take my leaue. <hi>Modbury in Deuon.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips reſpectiuely, SAM. HIERON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16518:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. TIM. 4.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I haue fought a good fight.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE beginning of this chapter<note n="a" place="margin">v. 1.2.3.4.</note> preſents vnto vs a very graue and ſoleme charge giuen as in the name of God and his moſt glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence by the Apoſtle vnto his <hi>Sonne</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">ver. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Timotheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The occaſion of the words.</note> that conſidering the euil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the times, &amp; the aptnes of men to turne <hi>their eares from the truth vnto Fables,</hi> he ſhould ſhew forth an extraordinarie and vnwearied induſtry in the faithfull execution of his publique Miniſtry. The reaſon inducing <hi>Paul</hi> to be at this time eſpecially ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement in this kind of perſwading, and which ſhould alſo moue <hi>Timothie</hi> to be as apt to entertaine the aduiſe, was the neeere approching of the time of his finall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; <hi>I am now readie to be offered, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">v. 6.</note> as if he had ſaid: <hi>I am vncertaine how ſoone the thred of my life may be cut eff, ſure</hi> I <hi>am, it cannot be stretched out long, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whileſt</hi> I <hi>haue time, (and for ought I knowe this may be the laſt time</hi> (I <hi>cannot but advertiſe thee:</hi> And <hi>ſeeing that which</hi> I <hi>now speake,</hi> I <hi>speake as one readie to lay downe this Tabernacle, in the depth of my affection to thee, and in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie of my heart to God, (before whom I exspect hourely to appeare) thine cares ought with the greater greedines euen to drinke in theſe my last words, &amp; they ſhould ſo farre forth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thee, that thou ſhouldst lay them vp, and hide</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 119.11.</note> 
               <hi>them, and keepe them in the midſt of thy heart.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 4.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now the mentioning of death, albeit it worketh lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with Euill men, vnleſſe it bee either to the deading of their hearts, like <hi>Nabals (he was like a ſtone,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 25.37</note> ſaith the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16518:4"/> Text), or to the making of them more deſperate ſecure, (<hi>Let vs eate and drink, for to morow we ſhall die,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">i. Cor. 15.32.</note> yet in ſuch a <hi>fleſhy</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ezech. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>melting</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2 Kin. 22.19.</note> 
               <hi>renewed</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 51.10.</note> heart as <hi>Paules</hi> was, it could not chuſe but leaue ſome impreſſion. For how could it be, that Paul, knowing, that when man returneth to his earth<note n="l" place="margin">Pſ. 146.4.</note> his ſpirit is eftſoones either receiued into <hi>euerlaſting Habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 16.9.</note>, or elſe diſmiſſed to be reſerued in <hi>chaines vnder darkenes, vnto the iudgement of the great day,</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iud. 6.</note> ſhould not alſo caſt with himſelfe, which of theſe two ſhould be the finall iſſue of his ſoule? Now then, beholding with the eies of his minde, the <hi>Glory that ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſhewed</hi> hereafter<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> on the one ſide, and the <hi>Burning Lake which is the ſecond Death</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Reu. 21.8.</note> on the other ſide, and knowing that each of them is by the ordinance of God, (as with a chaine of Adamant) tyed to the holynes or profanes of the former courſe, therefore for the ſecuring of his owne ſoule, for the encouraging his pupill <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and for a ſauing and comfortable directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs all, he ioyfully lookes back into his life by paſt, that from thence he may deriue a hopefull inference for the time to come: <hi>I haue fought a good fight &amp;c, From hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is laide vp for me &amp;c.</hi> Thus with as much fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and plainenes as I could, I haue let you ſee, the courſe, and order, and dependance of this Text. It is a notable and a pregnant proofe of the ſaying of the wiſe man, (<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 14.32.</note>) <hi>The wicked ſhalbe caſt away for his malice, but the Righteous hath hope in his death.</hi> That <hi>Pauls Hope</hi> was not in this <hi>life onely</hi> (<note n="r" place="margin">Cor. 15.19.</note>) appeareth by the folowing verſe: what were the grounds of his hope, by which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>a Hope not making aſhamed</hi> (<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note>) is declared in this verſe. It is borne vp with three ſupporters. 1. <hi>A Good fight</hi> well diſcharged: <hi>2.</hi> a holy Courſe well finiſhed. 3. a ſound Faith well preſerued. This is like Salomons <hi>threefold cord</hi> (<note n="t" place="margin">Ecc. 4.12.</note>) which is not <hi>eaſely broken.</hi> It may be compared to that <hi>Skarlet cord</hi> (<note n="u" place="margin">Ioſ. 2.</note>) by which <hi>Rahab</hi> let downe the ſpyes, and which ſhee left hanging in her window. For as that was the marke by which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16518:4"/> her houſe was knowne, and ſhee ſaued from the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Iericho,</hi> ſo this holy Twine, is a pledge to that ſoule where the Lord hath tyed it, that it ſhal be freed from the wrath that is to come. Time will not giue leaue to vntwiſt euery ſpecialty. I will proceed as I may, and beginne with the firſt, praying you all that inaſmuch as the ſame diſſolution of nature awaites vs all, which hath long ſince brought Paul to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected Reſt, we would yeeld our ſelues to be ſo farre forth perſwaded by that, which by Gods aſſiſtance I ſhall ſpeake, that by ſeeking to imitate <hi>Pauls</hi> hope, we may at laſt partake the ſame happines which <hi>Paul</hi> doth.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the more exact diſcouerie of the hidde Treaſure of this my Text,<note n="d" place="margin">Doctrine out of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the place.</note> 
               <hi>I</hi> muſt commend vnto you this generall obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, grounded vpon the courſe and order of this Place, namely, <hi>That the moſt ſolide com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to a Chriſtian ſoule, beholding the greiſly and ghaſtly countenance of approching Death, is the Teſtimony which the Heart beareth to it ſelfe, of the former ſteady care to walke in all good conſcience before God.</hi> I would be loth to be charged with offering violence to my Text, therefore I will let you ſee how this doctrine ariſeth kindly and vn-enforced from this ſcripture. Wee ſee firſt our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in a reſolued expectation of his now very neere at hand departure: that is expreſſe, we ſee him alſo aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe of no ſmaller honour then a Crowne of Righteouſnes: ſo much the verſe following will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs to denie. If it be demaunded now, whence it was, that his thoughts of death were ſo full of comfort, and his hopes of happines ſo full of confidence, the trueſt anſwer is this, it came even from hence, that the witnes in his boſome, ſpeaking the truth before the <hi>Witnes in heauen,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 16.19.</note> teſtified with him and for him, that in all his courſe from the very firſt inſtant of his conuerſion, vnto this laſt concluſion and ſhutting vp of his daies, his whole drift was, in <hi>ſimplicity and godly purenes to haue his Conuerſation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16518:5"/> in the World</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Cor. 1.12.</note>. <hi>I haue fought a good fight. I haue finiſhed my courſe, &amp;c.</hi> So that, this conſidered, there is very ſufficient footing for this doctrine, in this Text. Giue me leaue to ſhew you in an example or two, how others of Gods holy ones, being guided by the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, haue in the like caſe, grounded their hopes vpon the like foundation. Note well the example of <hi>Hezekiah</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſ. 38.1. &amp;c.</note>. He knew generally by natures inſtinct, that he muſt die; but at this time (I now ſpeake of) the prophet of the Lord, euen the prophet Iſaiah came vnto him with this dolefull meſſage. <hi>Put thine houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die and not liue.</hi> Whom would not theſe tidings haue ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the heart, and what could <hi>Hezakiah</hi> expect but preſent death? well then, all things threatning his end, the common condition of nature, the mortality of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſicknes (being, as it is thought, the plague) and aboue all, the doome come from the Lord by the hand of ſuch a prophet, where was the ſtaffe of <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> comfort, but euen as our Apoſtles was in the ſecret witnes of his owne ſoule, teſtifiing vnto him the ſincerity and holines of his former courſe? <hi>O Lord remember now how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which was good in thy fight.</hi> Who ſo compareth this of <hi>Paul,</hi> with that of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> muſt needs ſay that they were both euen the very breathings of one and the ſame ſpirit. Thinke we that <hi>Eliïah,</hi> ſitting vnder the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper tree</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1. Kin. 19.4.10.</note> could with any comfort haue deſired the Lord, <hi>to take his ſoule,</hi> if he had not had his aſſurance <hi>written vpon the table of his heart</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 3.3.</note> that he had bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <hi>very iealous for the Lord God of hoſts? Could old Simeon</hi> with a glad ſpirit haue beſought the Lord euen inſtantly to diſmiſſe him, if his conſcience had not told him, that all his life paſt had bene an intentiue awaiting for <hi>the Conſolation of Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 2.2.25.26.</note>. But what ſhould I ſearch the ſcripture for more examples? <hi>Looke to Ieſus the author and finiſher of our Faith,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 12·2.</note> and ſee whether, when he a as <hi>man made ſinne for vs</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> was to drink that bitter <hi>Cup</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> and to taſte death for vs all<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 2.9.</note>, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant expectation of parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16518:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> with his fathers glory, came not by the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees vnto the due perfection? Examine that effectuall prayer compoſed by him the night before his ſuffrings, when he <hi>knew that his houre was come that he ſhould depart out of this world vnto the Father</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 13.1.</note>. <hi>Read Ioh.</hi> 17.5.6. <hi>I haue glorified thee, now glorifie me, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you demaund a reaſon of this Doctrine,<note place="margin">The reaſon of the Doct.</note> you may thus conceiue it, and I pray you to marke it, leaſt I ſhould be miſtaken and thought to place mans hope of comfort in himſelfe. A man which iourneyeth, builds his aſſurance of ſafe arriuing at the place he aimeth at, vpon his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to enquire, and his care to keepe the right path leading thereunto. <hi>The place I intend, I knowe, the way</hi> I <hi>am well aduiſed of, in it I am ſure I am,</hi> I <hi>haue traueiled in it as was fit, therefore I am ſure I ſhall not faile in my intent.</hi> This is a kinde of reaſoning which cannot deceiue. So is it in this caſe. The way to heauen is Chriſt. I am the way.<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.</note> by his bloud he hath tracked out for vs <hi>a new and liuing way</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note>: For the help of his choſen in this way, he hath giuen his <hi>word: He hath ſhewed thee, O man what is good, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mic· 6.8.</note>. to his word he hath annexed Miniſters, as <hi>Guides</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 8.31.</note> for vnderſtanding it: with the voice of his word he hath coupled the Teaching of his ſpirit: <hi>Thine eares ſhall heare a word behinde thee, ſaying. This is the way, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iſ. 30.21.</note>. He hath ſet marks alſo in the way, by which to know it; as namely, <hi>1.</hi> Antiquity <hi>Stand in the waies and aske for the old way, which is the good way, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note>. 2. <hi>Purity. There ſhalbe a path and a way, and the way ſhalbe called Holy, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Iſ. 35.8.</note>. 3. Fruitfulnes. <hi>He hath ordained good works that we ſhould walke in them</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note>. 4. Straitnes, and the fewnes of paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. <hi>The gate is ſtrait and the way narrow which leadeth to life, and few there be that finde it</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Math. 7.14.</note>. So then, the marke I haue alwaies aimed at is heauen, euen the <hi>Price of the high calling of God in Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note>: the way to it I haue ſought, not in mine owne heart, nor in the guiſes and humors of the world, but in the Scripture: I haue found it to be Faith in Chriſt working by loue<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> and making a man
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16518:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>zealous of goodworks</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14.</note>: to this way my heart hath bene ſet<note n="u" place="margin">Deu. 32.46.</note>, it hath bene my continuall and inſtant <hi>ſuite to be directed in this Path</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 119.36.</note> and though with much weaknes, <hi>and limping</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 12.13.</note>, yea and <hi>falling</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 37.24.</note> ſometimes, yet to it I <hi>haue ſtriuen</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Luc. 13.24.</note> 
               <hi>continually:</hi> How then without calling Gods truth and faithfulnes into Queſtion, can I doubt of the End, when my conſcience is witnes with me, that my ſteady <hi>reſpect</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 119.6.</note> hath bene vnto the way guiding thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? you ſee then the truth of the doctrine, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it, and withall that in it there is no building vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues, but a hopefull reſting vpon the Lord, who hauing <hi>taught</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 119.33.</note> me the way, and <hi>enclined my heart</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ver. 36.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> me in it<note n="d" place="margin">Ver. 116.</note>, I know him to be ſo farre from <hi>denying himſelfe</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.13.</note> that I cannot miſſe of the end of my courſe, the <hi>ſaluation</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.9.</note> of my ſoule. This the piety, the Purity, the ſincerity of my former courſe, ſecureth me of the Glory to come, not becauſe of any connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt worke and wages, which I truſt vnto, but becauſe the Lord, <hi>of his owne will</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iam. 1.18.</note> and free grace, hath vouchſafed the <hi>ſinglenes</hi> of my <hi>heart</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 6.5.</note>, <hi>purged from dead works by the blood of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> euen amidſt many weakneſſes to be the way to lead me vnto life. So that my title is the promiſe<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 3.18.</note> of God, and not mine owne performance: the conſcience of my former courſe, is the aſſurer, not the deſeruer of my happines. Some great man out of his bounty giueth the an inheritance of ſome pounds by the yeare, thou muſt pay a pepper corne for thy Rent; when thou haſt paid it, indeed thou maiſt claime the profits, yea and by lawe thou maiſt recouer them: but what wilt thou plead? what? that thou art worthy of it, that thou haſt paid well for it? no: the bargaine is thy plea, the couenant is all which thou canſt alleadge, for betwixt the rent and the revenue there is no proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo, for thy <hi>Graine of muſterdſeed</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Math. 17.20.</note> 
               <hi>thy Smooking</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Jſ 42.3.</note> and ſcarſe appearing Faith, thy ſcant Obedience, thy <hi>Cup of cold water</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Math. 10.42.</note> thou maiſt challenge heauen, and God will not, God cannot denie it thee, yea he loueth to be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16518:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo vrged: but yet thou canſt not ſay, <hi>It is mine, I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it:</hi> (for what is all this to that <hi>ſurpaſſing, exceeding, eternall weight of Glory</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note>, but, <hi>O Lord it is mine, thou haſt promiſed it.</hi> Thus you ſee how without any preiudicing, nay rather how with the enlarging of the Riches of Gods grace, the comfort of a dying Chriſtian, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the witnes of his conſcience touching the ſinceritie of his heart, and the vnblameable cariage of his life.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine is plaine and obuious to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans conceiuing, and it muſt needes be this,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> euen to warne vs all, as we tender our owne ſoules comfort at the inſtant of Natures diſſolution, ſo to be very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding of our preſent courſe, that out of it we may raiſe our hopes, that when <hi>our earthly houſe of this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle ſhalbe deſtroied, we ſhall haue a building giuen vs of God, eternall in the heauens</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note>, that the conſcience of our <hi>vnlawfull deedes and vncleanly conuerſation</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.7.8.</note> may not fill our faces with ſhame and our hearts with horror, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king death to be vnto vs <hi>The King of feare</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 18.14.</note> and the thought of Gods preſence, (before whom we ſhall then vnderſtand, that we are ſhortly to appeare) as a pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto eternall miſery. Certaine it is, that whatſoeuer we now in our ſecuritie (through Satans bewitching) doe imagine bleſſing our ſelues ſecretly, and ſaying we ſhall haue peace<note n="ſ" place="margin">Deu. 29.19.</note>, yet as ſure as God liueth, who hath ſaid in his word, that <hi>the light of the wicked ſhall be quenched</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iob. 18.5.</note> and <hi>the hope of the vniuſt periſh</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pro. 11.7.</note>, ſo ſurely ſuch as hath beene our courſe, ſuch ſhalbe our end, if we haue liued without conſcience, we ſhall ſurely die without comfort. And to ſet the better edge vpon this advertiſement, giue me leaue to draw you a little into the conſideration of that thing, as if it were now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which ere long will indeede be preſent. We are met here togither at this time (by Gods prouidence) men of ſundrie faſhions and of diuers ranks, but (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer differing otherwiſe) all by profeſſion, Chriſtians
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16518:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> and by condition, mortall. All our teeth are ſet on edge, with the fruite which Adam eate, and the law of death, is heauens decree and cannot be revoked. Well, put caſe we were inſtantly arreſted with ſome killing ſicknes, (the herauld of approaching death) and were to looke backe into that part of the wallet (as the prouerb ſaith) which is behinde, to ſee what hopes for future quiet, we are able to deriue out of our former conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: let vs (I ſay) conſider well and deale faithfully with our ſelues, whether our faſhion of life by-paſt, be not more like to fill vs with diſcouragements, and to breed in vs a <hi>fearefull looking for of Iudgement</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 10.27.</note> then to embolden vs with a holy reſolution to exſpect a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous admittance into our <hi>Maſters Ioy</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Math. 15.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. And indeede when men in the records of their owne conſciences, ſhall read written in great letters, the profaneſſe, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, the contempt of religion, the ſcorne of Gods word, the ignorance, the Monſtrous oathes, the vicious ſpeakings, the cruelties, the oppreſſions, the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the abuſe of Gods creatures, &amp; the whole troupes of groſſe ſinnes, which haue beene in a manner the very buſines of their daies, what can they exſpect, but that their death, ſhould be like the mans eſtate of whome the prophet<note n="y" place="margin">Amos. 5.19.</note> ſpeaketh, who <hi>did flee from a Lion and a Beare met him,</hi> ſo ſhould their dying alſo be, a diſcharge from a wretched world, but withall an entrance into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother woe, euen an endles, eaſles, hopeles miſery? It is a ſure Maxime in diuinitie, that the future, both happines and Miſerie, are begun in this preſent world: ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and holmes are the firſt fruites of the one: impietie and profanes the beginnings of the other. The Saints by election are <hi>Saintes by calling</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.2.</note>: their <hi>conuerſation is now in heauen</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> whoſe future portion is in heauen. <hi>That which God hath coupled together let no man put aſunder</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 19.6.</note>. you will plead againſt me, that ſo much abuſed exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the conuerted theife at the point of execution<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 23.39</note>. I anſwer. Firſt, he began to worke, as ſoone as he was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16518:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> called: he bewailed his ſinne<note n="d" place="margin">v. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, he confeſſed Chriſt<note n="e" place="margin">verſ. 41.42.</note>, he aduiſed his fellow Thiefe<note n="f" place="margin">ver. 40.</note>: ſecondly, the example was extraordinary (for the gracing of Chriſts then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement) ſhewing what God can doe, not what ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily he will doe. I haue ſeene a pardon giuen to a man vpon the gallowes, but who ſo emboldeneth himſelfe therevpon, perhaps the rope may be his hire: it is not good to put it vpon the Pſalme of <hi>Miſerere,</hi> and the neck-verſe, for ſometime he prooues no clark. God once made an Aſſe to ſpeake<note n="g" place="margin">Numb. 23.28.</note>, but he that ſhould therefore ſpurre his beaſt, till he ſpake alſo, all men would condemne him for vnwiſe. Let then this be the concluſion. The refreſhing of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit, when his departing approched, was the conſcience of his well-run courſe: a Chriſtian by calling, a Chriſtian by conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, could not but haue a Chriſtians inheritance. <hi>Goe &amp; doe thou likewiſe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 10.37.</note>. Let the life of the religious be thy ſtudy, and <hi>the death of the righteous</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Num. 23.10.</note> ſhalbe thy ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; where there hath beene the <hi>firſt reſurrection</hi> there can be no <hi>ſecond death</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Reu. 20.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered generally of the grounds of <hi>Pauls</hi> hope, his cariage paſt: now let vs examin it more particularly: and firſt, of the firſt ſupporter. I <hi>haue fought a good fight.</hi> What then (will ſome man ſay to me) was <hi>Paul</hi> a ſouldier, that he ſpeakes here of <hi>fighting?</hi> yes, hee was a ſouldier, and the ſame no freſh-water, or white-liuered ſouldier, but a valiant, experienced, and beaten champion, one that had paſſed the hazard of many skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, and (as teſtimonies of his hardy courage,) was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhew the ska<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res of many receiued wounds, <hi>I beare in my bodie the markes of the Lord Ieſus</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gal 6.17.</note>. But as the things we now diſcourſe of are ſpirituall things, ſo this fighting muſt be vnderſtood in a ſpirituall ſenſe. <hi>Paule a ſpirituall man</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.16.</note>, his aduerſaries ſpirituall, or for ſpirituall reſpects, his weapons ſpirituall<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4.</note>, his victories ſpirituall. Let mee acquaint you with particulars, that ſo the vſe of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be the more full.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16518:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Paules fights.</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> vndergoeth a double conſideration: 1. either as a Chriſtian, or ſecondly, as an Apoſtle and Miniſter of Chriſt Ieſus: ſome of his fightings, more properly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne his eſtate as a Chriſtian: ſome againe he was more eſpecially tryed in by vertue of his calling. As he was a Chriſtian, I find in his owne writings the report of two e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall conflicts: the one <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. betwixt Nature and Grace, the Spirit and the fleſh, the lawe of his members, and the lawe of God. Who ſo reades and examineth the place, ſhall ſee firſt the qualitie of the combatants, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the grounds and termes of the quarell, thirdly, the hazard (as might ſeeme for the time) and doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the euent, together with ſome foyles taken on either part, and laſtly the certaintie and comfort of the victorie, <hi>I thanke God through Ieſus Christ our Lord</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ver. 25.</note>. The ſecond combate is, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and that was more direct and immediat with Sathan, although he therein cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as his vſe is) wrought vpon the advantage of <hi>Paules</hi> corruption. In this, <hi>Paul</hi> was much toſſed, and goared, and buffeted, and glad to flie once, and againe, and the third time for refuge to the Lord. Howbeit, though the aſſault was ſharpe, yet the conqueſt was great. <hi>My grace ſhall be ſufficient for thee</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ver. 9.</note>, and <hi>Very gladly will I reioyce in mine infirmities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now his <hi>fightings</hi> (as an Apoſtle) were diuers, and the ſame not idle or cauſeleſſe, about needleſſe <hi>Queſtions and ſtrife of words</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.4.</note>, <hi>for ſo fight I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not as one beating the ayre</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.26.</note>: but they were graue and weightie, euen for the ſucceſſe of his miniſterie, and the enlargement of the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus. They may (for teachings ſake) be thus diſtinguiſhed: to haue bene either againſt the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and vnſound cavillings, or againſt the violences and cruelties of thoſe which were aduerſaries to the truth. Of the former ſort, we haue his combate with <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> at <hi>Paphus</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Act. 13.</note>, with the reuiuers of the legall ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at <hi>Antioch</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 15.</note>, with the Stoickes and Epicures at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 17.</note>, with thoſe <hi>Beaſts</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32</note>, <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his faction at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16518:8"/>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Act. 19.</note>, with <hi>Hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.14</note>, with <hi>Alexander</hi> the Smith<note n="z" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1</note>. With all theſe, and with many beſides theſe he combated, and ouer all theſe <hi>through the helpe of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note>, he had the victorie. For it may be truly ſaid of them all, which himſelfe ſpeaketh of ſome, <hi>their madneſſe was made euident vnto all man, and they preuayled not long.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.9.</note> His <hi>figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings</hi> with the violences and cruelties of euill men, it were long to particularize. I referre you to his owne report<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 11.23. &amp;c.</note>. In all theſe he was <hi>more then Conqueror</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note>, and by none of theſe was either his comfort impeached, his miniſterie and cauſe endammaged, or the Church of God damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Not his comfort impeached, for <hi>We faint not, but though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed dayly</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.16.</note>. Not his miniſterie and cauſe endammaged: for, albeit <hi>I ſuffer vnto bonds, yet the word of God is not bound</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.9.</note>, and <hi>the things which haue come vnto me are turned to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the Goſpell</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Phil. 1.12.</note>; laſtly, not the Church of God damnified, for, I <hi>ſuffer all things for the elects ſake</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.10</note>, and <hi>many of the brethren are emboldened through my bands, and dare more frankely ſpeake the word</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 1.14.</note>. Thus I haue giuen you a briefe of <hi>Pauls</hi> fightings, and of <hi>Pauls</hi> victories; ſharpe encounters, glorious conqueſts. Theſe were they, the remembrance wherof made the face of death euen loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto him, and confirmed his inward certaintie of the <hi>Recompence of reward</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note>, euen becauſe he was able to ſay in truth of conſcience, <hi>I haue fought a good fight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This farre for the opening of the text, and the laying the grounds of that which I would ſay, I haue reported to you things done, I come now to ſpeake of things to be done. For this clauſe (as all other holy Scripture) is <hi>for our learning</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note>, and <hi>is profitable to teach</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16</note>. I will bound my whole ſpeech within the compaſſe of theſe two points: firſt, I will ſhew that all Chriſtians are called to the like fight: ſecondly, I will draw to an inquitie by way of application of the whole,<note place="margin">Euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian called to the like fight, that Paule fought.</note> how farre foorth we haue fought this fight.</p>
            <p>For proofe of the former, if men were (as they ought to be) experienced in the Scriptures, I need alledge no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16518:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> more then the Apoſtles exhortation to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> where he calleth them to the <hi>hauing of the ſame fight, which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you haue ſeene in me, and now heare to be in me</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Phil. 1.30.</note>. But for the ſatisfaction of all, I will ſhew you the truth of it by points and parcels. Firſt, touching the fight, in a mans owne boſome, euen in his owne heart, with his owne corruption. <hi>Paul</hi> deliuereth this generall rule cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching all Gods choſen, that in them <hi>the fleſh luſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> accords, that <hi>the luſts of the fleſh do fight againſt the ſoule</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.11.</note>. The gift of Regeneration (meant by <hi>ſpirit</hi>) and the corruption of nature (vnderſtood by <hi>Fleſh</hi>) are mixed togither (like the light and darkenes in the aire, in the dawning,<note n="*" place="margin">Quod tu nec tenebras, nec poſſis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere lucem. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</note> ſo throughout in all the powers of the ſoule,) and theſe two being in a direct line of oppoſition and contrariety ech to other, there muſt needs follow a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall combate, like the ſtrugling which <hi>Rebecca</hi> felt in her wombe<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> making a Chriſtian crie in a kinde of aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as ſhee did, <hi>why am I thus?</hi> Happy he which feeles this combate, who is euer wraſtling with his owne corruption, labouring and <hi>endeauouring himſelfe to haue a cleere conſcience toward God</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note>. The victory is certaine: For as it was ſaid to <hi>Rebecca</hi> when vpon the ſtriuing ſhee felt, ſhee asked of God, that the <hi>elder</hi> ſhould <hi>ſerue the younger,</hi> ſo in this caſe we are aſcertained that <hi>the old man,</hi> (our old naturall corruption) ſhalbe <hi>caſt of and killed,</hi> and the <hi>new man</hi> (the grace wrought by Gods ſpirit) <hi>created in righteouſnes and true holines</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eph. 4.22.24.</note> ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be more and more eſtabliſhed. Secondly touching <hi>the Fight</hi> with <hi>Sathan,</hi> the ſcripture is expreſſe. <hi>He hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired you to win now you</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iuc. 22.31.</note> ſaid Chriſt to <hi>Peter, and he walketh about ſeeking to deuoure,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> to vs<note n="u" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> well <hi>reſiſt him</hi> we muſt: it is S. <hi>Iames</hi> his rule<note n="*" place="margin">Ch. 4.7.</note> and that cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fighting: and it is not <hi>fleſh and bloud, we wraſtle with,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle, but <hi>principalities and powers, &amp;c.</hi> and we had need to prouide, that we may <hi>ſtand faſt</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Eph. 6.12 13.</note>. He is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16518:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> but a titular Chriſtian, and hath but a <hi>ſhew of godlines</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5.</note>, who hath not had perſonall experience of the Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemes of Sathan, now puffing vp to preſumption, now pulling downe to deſpaire, one while working to ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, another while preſſing to diſmayedneſſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times extenuating, and hiding, and painting ſinne, that before it is committed it may beguile, ſometimes ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and aggrauating it, that when it is performed, it may affright: turning himſelfe into many ſhapes, ſometimes like an induſtrious agent to aduance our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, ſometimes like a pleaſant companion, to further our delight, ſometimes like a true-hearted friend, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect our good name, but alwaies a venimous aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to empoyſon our ſoule. Theſe are no new things to the children of God: the mercie of God, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Sathan, they know them well to be vndiuided companions. Neither is the Scripture wanting to aſſure vs of the conqueſt. It was ſaid of old, that the ſerpent, his head being broken, could <hi>but bruiſe the heele</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note>, and it hath bene a freſh renewed, that <hi>Greater is he which is in vs, then he which is in the world</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Job. 4.4.</note>, and we all, ſo many as are now in the liſts againſt this aſſaylant haue this warrant, ſealed (ſeeing it is a part of the new Teſtament) with the bloud of Chriſt, <hi>that the God of peace ſhall tread Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than vnder our feet ſhortly</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 16.20</note>. The third fight is for the maintenance of the cauſe of Religion, againſt both the cunning of oppoſers, and the malice of perſecutors. That euery Chriſtian is to fight with a holy zeale for the purity of religion, <hi>S. Iude</hi> ſhall witneſſe for me, <hi>It was needfull for me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to write vnto you, to exhort you that you ſhould earneſtly contend for the faith which was once giuen to the Saints</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iude 3.</note>. <hi>The kingdome of heauen</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 11.12.</note> There is force in getting the truth, there muſt be a kind of force alſo in maintaining it. <hi>Dauid</hi> choſe religion for his <hi>heritage</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 119.111</note>. He is not worthie to haue it, which will not ſtriue to preſerue it. Now for this kind of fight there
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16518:10"/> are two things required: Firſt, skill: and ſecondly, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. Skill, becauſe euery corner is ſo full of cunning and ſubtill vnderminers of religion: Atheiſts, Ieſuits, Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Sectaries: theſe fight not with violence and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed enmitie, but with plauſible reaſons, with ſmooth perſwaſions, and with all the glozing pretences which hell can deuiſe to entangle. What need haue men then of <hi>exerciſed wits</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note>, <hi>and vnderſtanding hearts</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 King. 3.9.</note>, knowing how wiſely to handle that ſame <hi>ſword of the ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.17.</note> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them? How requiſite is it, that Chriſtian ſouldiers ſhould be daily practiſing the feates of ſpirituall armes, that they may know how to grapple with the aduerſarie at euery kind of weapon, and to make their part good againſt euery encounter? As ſkill is required, ſo cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and reſolution alſo: for know you, what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid to the conuerted Hebrewes<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 10.32.</note>, <hi>After ye receiued light,</hi> (that is, ſome ſauing knowledge and feeling of the truth) <hi>ye endured a great fight of afflictions:</hi> Is not be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> need of courage? what thinke we of the <hi>Mockings of Iſmael</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 21.9.</note>, the diſdaine of <hi>Herod</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Luk. 23.11.</note>, the <hi>ſcourgings of Pilate</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 27.26.</note>, of <hi>ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of goods, of being made a gazing ſtocke by reproches</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 10.33.34.</note>, nay, of <hi>reſiſtance to bloud</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 12.4.</note>? Do not theſe things require a reſolution? were it not fitting that, we ſhould be well prouided, who muſt go through all theſe bicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, leſt when we haue ſtrooke a ſtroake or two, we ſhould be <hi>wearied and faint</hi> in our minds<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 12.3.</note>, and ſo be like the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> of whom the Pſalme ſaith<note n="q" place="margin">Iſ. 78.9.</note>, that <hi>being armed and ſhooting with the bowe, they turned backe in the day of battell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the neceſſitie of this kind of <hi>Eight</hi> for the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the cauſe of Religion, lieth vpon all, ſo vpon two degrees eſpecially, Magiſtrates and Miniſters. They are both called <hi>Leaders</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Sam. 9.16. Vnges eum anteceſſorem. Hebr. 13.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the people, and therefore as of <hi>Leaders,</hi> whoſe experience muſt inſtruct, and whoſe valour muſt encourage and put heart into others, there is twiſe ſo much required. It is their office to <hi>ſtand in the breach</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſa. 106.23.</note>, and to <hi>goe out and in</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. King. 3.7.</note> before the people,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16518:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> and to beare the ſhock and brunt of the firſt grapling. If they be ſound and ſincere, inſtant and reſolute in the cauſe of God, oh, what life and courage ſhall they put into the multitude which doe euen depend vpon their conduct? if they be cold and daſtardly and giue ground in the day of battell, how will they make the hearts of the people euen to die within them, and what hope will Sathan haue to ſet vp his ſtandard in the midſt of Gods church? But as the egernes in this combate is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of Magiſtrates and Miniſters more then of others, ſo of vs who be Miniſters moſt of all. In the old Law things in the ſanctuarie were double to that which was common, the Shekell of the ſanctuary twice ſo weightie as the common ſhekell<note n="u" place="margin">Ex. 30.13.</note>, the cubit of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie twice ſo long as the common cubit<note n="*" place="margin">Compare 1 Kin. 7.15. with 2. Chro 3.15.</note>. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had neede to wiſh as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did of <hi>Eliah,</hi> his <hi>spirit</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">2. King. 2.9.</note>, that the ſpirit of vnderſtanding and courage may be doubled and trebled vpon him. If he be the man, as he ſhould be, Sathan oweth him a double ſpite, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny combates with the Church of God, he ſeemeth to giue like charge to his Inſtruments, which the king of Aram gaue to his ſouldiers<note n="y" place="margin">1. Kin. 22.31.</note> 
               <hi>Eight neither with ſmall nor great, ſaue onely againſt the King of Iſrael:</hi> For he thinketh that if he can ſmite the ſhepheard, with a ſpirit either of Error, or of drowzines, or of ambition, or of avarice, <hi>the ſheepe of the flock ſhall be quickly ſcattered</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Math. 26.31.</note>. He knoweth by long experience, that <hi>from the Prophets of Ieruſalem wickednes goeth forth into all the Land</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 23.15.</note>, and that if <hi>the Light</hi> which God hath ſet in his Church be <hi>darkenes, the darkenes cannot</hi> but exceede<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 6.23.</note>. Thus I haue ſhewed you the particulars of <hi>Pauls Fightings,</hi> and the neceſſitie of the ſame <hi>Fight,</hi> in euery one of vs that would be (as we are called) Chriſtians: nowe let vs come to the next points, the Inquirie how on our parts this <hi>Fight</hi> hath beene performed, <hi>viz.</hi> how we haue fought againſt Corruption, how we haue fought againſt Sathan, how we haue ſtriuen and fought for the vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16518:11"/> and maintenance of Gods Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An enquiry how we haue fought this fight.</note>And here, in the very firſt entry of my Meditations, when I did in my thoughts compare together thoſe which doe <hi>Fight</hi> this good <hi>Fight</hi> vnder the banner of the Lord of Hoſtes, with thoſe, who (whatſoeuer their profeſſion is) doe indeede and intruth <hi>fight</hi> againſt him, it brought into my minde, that which the ſpirit of God reports touching the Iſraelitiſh troupes, and the armies of the Aramites their adverſaries<note n="c" place="margin">1. Kin. 20.27.</note>. <hi>The children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael pitched before them, like two litle flocks of Kids,</hi> but the Aramites <hi>filled the Country:</hi> the very like compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be truely made betwixt thoſe which <hi>fight</hi> on the Lords part, and thoſe which <hi>fight</hi> againſt him, or at the leaſt, (which by our ſauiours rule<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 11.23.</note> is all one) <hi>fight</hi> not with him: the one ſide (the better part <hi>I</hi> meane) are but even a handfull in reſpect, <hi>one of a citie, two of a Tribe</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 3.14.</note>, the other a numberleſſe number, and may well be titled with the name of the poſſeſſed<note n="f" place="margin">Marc. 5.9.</note>, <hi>Legion,</hi> for indeede they are <hi>Many.</hi> And therefore true will that be which was ſpoken of old by <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iſ. 10.21.22.</note> and hath beene ſince renued by <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 9.27.</note>, <hi>Though the number of the children of Iſrael</hi> (men profeſſing Religion) <hi>were as the ſand of the Sea, yet ſhall but a remnant be ſaued.</hi> It will not be inough to haue ſaid thus, vnleſſe it be confirmed alſo, <hi>I</hi> will therefore ſhew you how true it is by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
            <p>Touching fighting againſt mens owne perſonall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, there are (that out of many I may cull out the cheife) three things, which doe ſhew the number of ſuch <hi>Fighters</hi> to be but ſmall: The firſt is, the generall Ignorance of this point of holy doctrine, concerning the combating together of theſe two, Corruption and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, nature and grace in euery true Chriſtian. <hi>I</hi> am not ſo well acquainted with your ſpirituall eſtate that are here preſent, as to be able peremptorily to determine ought: yet perhaps) if a man ſhould deale with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of this aſſembly by polle, and ſhould examine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16518:11"/> them as ſtraitly as the <hi>Gileadites</hi> did the <hi>Ephraiimites,</hi> touching <hi>ſhibboleth</hi> and <hi>ſibboleth</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iud. 12.</note>, demaunding of each this queſtion, <hi>How fareth it with thee, touching the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of thine owne heart, preuaileth it or yeeldeth it to the power of Gods spirit? How goeth on the quarell betwixt the lawe of ſinne, and the law of God?</hi> perhaps (<hi>I</hi> ſay) this demaund would be quitted with ſuch an anſwer, as was that of <hi>Pauls.</hi> to the lately conuerted diſciples at <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Act 19.2.</note> 
               <hi>Haue ye receiued</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye beleeued? And they ſaid, Wee haue not ſo much as heard whether there be an Holy Ghost.</hi> So in this caſe, they would ſay; <hi>you make a ſtraunge motion, we haue not ſo much as heard whether there be any ſuch contention:</hi> And it may be alſo, ſuch as haue ſome better vnderſtanding then the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, if in this particular they were well preſſed, would but make ſuch a confuſed anſwer as <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> did to <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">2. Sam. 18.29.</note>, <hi>Is the young man Abſalom ſafe,</hi> ſaid <hi>Dauid? I ſawe a great tumult, but</hi> I <hi>knewe not what,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ahimaaz;</hi> ſo they would be forced to ſay, <hi>Truth is,</hi> I <hi>haue heard or read ſomething of ſuch a matter, but I doe not diſtinctly and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally vnderstand it.</hi> Thus (as it was<note n="m" place="margin">Math. 26.73.</note> ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi>) mens very ſpeech bewrayeth them, and their dumbneſſe when they are asked the <hi>Word</hi> (as the ſouldiers call it) ſheweth them to be but ſtraglers and hangbies vpon the Lords campe, and no good <hi>Fighters:</hi> well, without iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging I leaue you, to to the <hi>accuſing</hi> or <hi>excuſing</hi> of your owne <hi>Thoughts</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note>: Onely this I ſay, that he which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with this point of doctrine, can no more be ſaid to be a <hi>Fighter</hi> in the <hi>good Fight</hi> againſt corruption and ſinne, then he can be reputed a partie in a caſe of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt two, who hath not ſo much as heard of the quarel. The 2. proofe that the <hi>Fighters</hi> on this ſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt corruption are but few is the vniuerſall yeelding of the moſt vnto corruption. When men come with bended knees, offring vp their weapons, yeelding themſelues to be ordred by thoſe whom they ſhould withſtand, there is no likelyhood that they haue an intent to <hi>Fight.</hi> So
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16518:12"/> in this caſe, when men generally haue (as it were) boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked their names, and entred into pay, and euen (as a man would thinke) ſworne their ſeruice to groſſe ſinnes, who will take them to be the Lords ſouldiers, or conceiue that there is any meaning in them to <hi>Fight</hi> againſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. And ſurely this is the common ſtate. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what <hi>Deborah</hi> in her ſong<note n="o" place="margin">Iud. 5.29.30.</note> reports of the mother of <hi>Siſera,</hi> how that ſhee and her ladies in their expectation of <hi>Siſera</hi> and his followers their returne in triumph, ſaid either to other (in their aſſurance of the victory) <hi>Haue they not gotten and diuided the ſpoile?</hi> I may ſay more truely (for that was ſpoken onely out of Imagination, either as they thought it was, or as they wiſhed it might be) of theſe foule enormities, which the word of God hath branded with the hatefull name, that they are the <hi>works of darkenes</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>Haue they not gotten and diuided the ſpoile?</hi> Do they not lead captiue, I ſay not as they did of <hi>Siſera, a maide or two,</hi> or (as <hi>Paul</hi> doth of the wily workemen of his time) a few <hi>ſimple women</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.6.</note>, but euen whole multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, of all rankes, of all callings, of all degrees? So often as I read thoſe places of ſcripture. <hi>The earth was corrupt before God and filled with cruelty</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 6.11.</note>, <hi>The men of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom compaſſed the houſe round about from the young euen to the old, all the people from all quarters</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 19.4.</note>, <hi>They aſſembled themſelues by companies into the harlots houſes</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ier. 5.7.</note>, <hi>From the leaſt euen to the greateſt of them, euery one is giuen to coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ier. 6.11.</note>, <hi>Then they stopped their eares, and ran vpon Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen all at once</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 7.57.</note>, <hi>Then aroſe a ſhout almoſt for the space of two houres of all men crying, Great is Diana of the Epheſians</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Act. 19.34.</note>, <hi>All ſeek their owne, and not that which is Ieſus Chriſts</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note>, ſo often (I ſay) as I read theſe and the like places, in which mention is made of ſwarmes of people ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues togither in euill, I cannot but reckon them as fore-tellings of theſe times, and theſe times as commentaries and expoſitions of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thoſe maſter-ſinnes, Ignorance, Contempt of the word and godlines, Security, and want of awe vnto
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16518:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gods maieſtie, Neglect of the worſhip of God, ſwearing, abuſe of the Sabaoth, Whoredome, Drunkeness, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Pride, Cruelty, Contention, Malice. &amp;c. marke how in euery towne in euery ſociety, in euery family almoſt, they doe euen ride in a kind of Triumph: if there be any better diſpoſed, labouring to be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the ſlaues of ſinne but to become the <hi>ſeruants of righteouſnes</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 6.20.</note>, they are as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe and ſuch as himſelfe<note n="a" place="margin">Iſ. 8.18</note> as <hi>ſignes</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and how the world entertaineth them it is knowne well inough: you know what <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 35.15.</note>, <hi>the abiects aſſembled themſelues, the falſe ſcoffers at banke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are me and ceaſed not;</hi> and againe, <hi>They that ſate in the gate spake of me, and the drunkards ſung of me</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſ. 69.12.</note>. This is the kindnes of this generation to thoſe who <hi>loue the Lord Ieſus in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 6.24.</note>. Thus the vniuerſall yeelding to corruption, men <hi>obeying ſinne in the Lusts thereof</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note>, <hi>and drawing it as with cartropes</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 5.18.</note> argueth that they <hi>fight not</hi> againſt <hi>ſinne.</hi> Euill <hi>raignes</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> in them and ouer them, they doe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly giue vp their members<note n="h" place="margin">ver. 13.</note> to folow it, and (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes) they <hi>take thought</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 13.14.</note> for it &amp; ſtudy to fulfil it. The third proofe in this part is, the <hi>Fight</hi> which is in the world for corruption: men doe not onely not <hi>fight</hi> againſt it, but they doe <hi>fight</hi> and ſtriue and labour to maintaine it. I remember what I read of <hi>Iehu</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Kin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.31.32.</note> the inſtrument of the Lords vengeance vpon <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe; as he entred in at the gate of <hi>Izreel,</hi> and lifting vp his eyes to the window, ſaw that painted <hi>Iezebel</hi> the wife of <hi>Ahab,</hi> he cryed out, <hi>who is on my ſide, who?</hi> preſently two or three of her attendants looked out, as it were offring their ſeruice. <hi>Caſt her downe</hi> (ſaith he) and they did ſo: ſo alſo in the chapter following, when he ſent to the guardians of <hi>Ahabs</hi> children, willing them, if they thought it good to create one of their maſters ſons King, and to ſtand vpon their guard, and they returned him anſwer, <hi>we are thy ſeruants and will doe all that thou ſhalt bid vs,</hi> what ſaid <hi>Iehu? If yea be mine and will obey my voyce, take
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16518:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the heads of your maſters ſonnes, and come to me to Izreel by to morrow this time.</hi> After the ſame ſort, we profeſſing our ſelues, by our outward ſhewes to be on the Lords ſide, and to be ready to doe all that he ſhall bid, his charge is, that if we be his, we caſt <hi>Iezebel</hi> out at the window, we renounce and diſclaime, we <hi>caſt of</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 4.22.</note> 
               <hi>and crucifie</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> our ſweetteſt, our deereſt, our profitableſt our beſt-pleaſing corruptions: <hi>Mortifie your members which are on earth</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note>. If we now ſhall not onely (contrary to commaund) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the life (which may be imputed to a kinde of nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and pitie) but ſhall <hi>fight</hi> for the life and ſtate of <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and ſhall ſet vp one of <hi>Ahabs</hi> ſonnes, ſome groſſe ſinne to raigne ouer vs, profeſſing our ſelues alwaies ready to defend it, how ſhall the Lord account vs to be his? And yet thus it fareth in theſe euill times. What ſinne, what groſſe corruption almoſt is there, which ſhall want a patrone to defend it, either that it is no ſinne, or that it is but a litle ſinne? This glauering and glozing age, which hath deuiſed an art to make defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med faces ſeeme faire, old wrincled viſages, to looke young and ſmooth, hath learned alſo to ſet a colour vpon naughtines, the diuell helping forward leaſt ſinne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in it owne proper likenes ſhould affright the conſcience. Thus the <hi>adulterous woman, wipeth her mouth, and ſaith,</hi> I <hi>haue committed noe Iniquity</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pro. 30.20.</note>. Euery vice doth now goe armed; if you doe touch it neuer ſo gently, yet (like the nettle) it wil ſting you; if you deale with it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly &amp; directly, it ſwaggreth like the <hi>hebrew</hi> with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who made thee a man of Authority</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Exo. 2.14.</note>? <hi>what? is this ſo great a matter? I truſt, this and this is lawfull, or if not, what need you be aggreeued?</hi> Thus men ſometimes like <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.13.</note> are not aſhamed to ſay they haue kept the commaundement of God, when they haue foulely broken it, ſometimes like the ſtubborne Iewes<note n="r" place="margin">Mal. 3.7.13.</note> crie <hi>wherein ſhall we returne,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in haue we treſpaſſed, <hi>what haue we ſpoken</hi> againſt God, when the very ſtones in the ſtreet are ready to teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and the earth is weary in bearing their ſinnes. And thus it appeareth by three vndeniable eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16518:13"/> that if we be endited before the Lord, for not <hi>fighting</hi> that <hi>Good fight</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> fought, and which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian ought to <hi>fight</hi> againſt ſinne and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhall neuer be able to plead <hi>Not-guilty.</hi> I wiſh that which hath bene ſaid may ſo conuict vs, that it may conuert vs, leaſt going on in rebellion againſt God, that doome befall vs which is foretold<note n="ſ" place="margin">Luc. 19.27</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe mine enemies, which would not that</hi> I <hi>ſhould raigne ouer them, bring them hither and ſlay them before me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as touching our failing in the ſecond fight which is againſt Sathan, conſidering what I haue alreadie ſaid, I ſhall need to ſpeake the leſſe: for where corruption and ſin are not withſtood, there Sathan is not fought againſt: where they are entertained, there Sathan is ſerued: ſo that the proofe of the former point, is a confirmation of this alſo. Neuertheleſſe, I will a litle inſiſt vpon one ſpecialtie, an apparant teſtimonie that there is litle thought or reſolution amongſt the moſt to fight againſt Sathan: and that is this, the neglect of one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall weapons whereby to encounter him. Thinke you that he meaneth to fight, who goeth vnarmed? nay, who when a weapon is tendred to him, caſts it from him, or who ſeemeth not to care, though it were with the land, as it was once with the ſtate of Iſrael vnder the Philiſtines<note n="t" place="margin">1. Sam. 13.19.22.</note>, of which it is ſaid, <hi>There was no Smith found throughout all the land,</hi> and, <hi>neither ſword nor ſpeare found in the hands of any of the people:</hi> he to whom this nakedneſſe were a pleaſure, or a matter of in differencie, would you imagine him to meane well, or to be a friend to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? I am ſure you would not. Now <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of the combate we are to haue with the diuell, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing by parcels, that holy armour wherewith he muſt be withſtood, mentioneth among other things, <hi>the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.27.</note>. This we ſee was our Sauiours weapon in that conflict which is ſtoried in the Goſpell<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 4.</note>: with this <hi>two edged ſword</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Reu. 1.16.</note> of <hi>It is written,</hi> he cut aſunder all thoſe knots, wherewith Sathans purpoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16518:14"/> was to entangle him. Who ſo then ſhall deſpiſe this wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, ſhall caſt it behind<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 50.17.</note> them, ſhall <hi>hate</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Prou. 1.22.</note> the knowledge of it, ſhall ſay to God, as the wicked are reported to do, <hi>Depart from vs, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iob 21.14.</note>, ſhall thinke preaching to be (as was ſaid<note n="b" place="margin">Ier. 23.33.</note> of old) <hi>The burden of the Lord,</hi> ſhall wiſh of it as the Gadarens did of Chriſt<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 8.34.</note>, that it might <hi>depart out of their coaſts:</hi> who ſo (I ſay) ſhall be thus affected, the charitableſt cenſure, and the moſt fauourable verdict which can be giuen of them is this, that they are wilfull betrayers of their owne ſoules into the power of the diuell. Now it is no hard matter, to ſhew, how deſeruedly, this Imputation may be laid vpon our times; I <hi>haue written vnto them</hi> (ſaid the Lord, of old, to the Iewes) <hi>the great things of my law, but they were counted as a ſtrange thing</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hoſ. 8.12.</note>. I doe not ſee how it can be denied, but that God may iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine ſo now, Great hath his kindneſſe bene to theſe times, in enlarging and improuing the free vſe of his word: and yet (alas) what a world of people is there amongſt vs, to whom the Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth as <hi>a booke that is ſealed vp</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 29.11.</note>, nay, (which is euen fearefull to thinke on) who ſeeme to be of that careles and neglecting humor, as though it were all one to them, though there had bene neuer any Bible written, nor any ſuch booke by the ſpeciall prouidence of God, preſerued to his Church? Againe, although the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God be entertained into ſome houſes, as a kind of needfull implement, to fill vp ſome corner, which otherwiſe might lie void, yet with many they are vſed like their harneſſe in theſe peacefull times, made a pray to the ruſt and duſt, or laid vp like the ſword of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> which <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke from him<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 21.9.</note>, like a monument, that it may be ſaid vpon occaſion, <hi>There they be.</hi> Few there be that do make them their <hi>Councellers</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſa. 119.24.</note>, or that do endeuour to hoſt them in their beſt roome, euen to let them <hi>dwell plenteouſly</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> in their hearts. Furthermore, for the opening and explaning thereof by thoſe whom
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16518:14"/> God hath deputed thereto, (which is, as it were, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rules and precepts of defence, teaching vs how to handle this weapon againſt our ſpirituall aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) how is it reckoned of? Where it is had, it is little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed; where it is wanting, it is leſſe deſired. Few doe reuerence it as Gods ordinance, few depend vpon it as vpon the <hi>arme</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iſ. 53.1.</note>, and <hi>power of God vnto ſaluation</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. What fighting can there be againſt Sathan, when this <hi>ſword of the ſpirit</hi> is in diſgrace? what ſpoile of ſoules will the diuell make, when men are not thus armed to reſiſt? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſtorie of <hi>Sampſon</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iud. 16.</note>. When the Philiſtines had taken him and put out his eyes, then they might do with him what they would, though he were a ſtrong man, and a noble man, yet they bound him with fetters, and made him grind like a horſe in a mill: and ſo when as the light of Gods holy ordinance is wanting, Sathan hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to worke his will: men may be drawne to any thing; no opinion ſo groſſe, no worſhip of God ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, no faſhion of life ſo vile, but they will ſoone embrace it. So then if our conſciences tell vs, that Gods word is not to vs, as it was to <hi>Ieremie</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 15.16.</note>, <hi>the ioy ioy and reioycing of our heart,</hi> that we are not like the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans, of whom it is ſaid, that when <hi>Philip</hi> came and preached among them, <hi>there was great ioy in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 8.8.</note>, nor like the man of Macedonia, which appeared to <hi>Paul</hi> in a viſion, and becauſe of the want of teaching which was there, prayed him <hi>to come to Macedonia and helpe</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> them, certainly we are no enemies vnto Sathans kingdome, but friends vnto it rather, if we labour not by all good meanes for the enlargement and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Gods truth.</p>
            <p>The laſt part of the enquirie concerneth the Fight for the maintenance of the common cauſe of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, both with ſkill againſt cunning and ſubtill vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners, and with courage againſt the wrongs and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which the world offereth to ſinceritie: I cannot now vſe that largeneſſe in this point, which I could wiſh,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16518:15"/> and which (the times conſidered) were very fitting. I will onely in a word touch two common euils, which ſhall ſerue to iuſtifie this propoſition, that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe which fight that part of that <hi>goood fight</hi> here ſpoken of, which concernes the vpholding and defence of Gods truth, is but ſmall and thin, euen like <hi>the Sommer gatherings,</hi> which the Prophet ſpeaketh of<note n="p" place="margin">Mic. 7.1.</note>. The one euill, is the want of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſoundneſſe of knowledge in the doctrine of religion. This is an vniuerſall and farre-ſpreading diſeaſe, according as euery Paſtor can witnes with me, who according to the Wiſe mans counſell<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 27.23.</note>, is <hi>diligent to know the eſtate of his flocke,</hi> and to vnderſtand the particular conceipts and diſpoſitions of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The multitude is wofully to ſeeke in matters of ſaluation, reſting to this day vpon that old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh rule, to follow the droane, and to beleeue as the Church beleeueth. I remember what is ſaid of a meeting of the people at Epheſus by <hi>Demetrius</hi> his procurement<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 19.32.</note>, <hi>The more part knew not wherefore they were come together:</hi> it may be truly ſaid ſo of many aſſemblies for holy ſeruices, the more part know not wherefore they come: they will ſay in generall termes to ſerue <hi>God;</hi> but, <hi>what he is, who he is, how to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, wherein to be ſerued, and in whome to be ſerued,</hi> I beleeue you ſhall finde them to be ignorant: So that the deuotions of many are like the Altar at Athens, <hi>To an vnknowne God</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Act. 17.23.</note> many are of <hi>Gallio</hi> his religion, of whome it is ſaid that he <hi>cared not for</hi> matters of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 18.17.</note>. If the bellie may be filled, and the back fitted, like the Epicure in the poet<note n="*" place="margin">Siventri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſilateri &amp;c. Hora.</note>, if with the fat-hearted Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, they may ſit <hi>by the fleſh-pots</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Exo. 16.3.</note>, and with thoſe whom <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>their wheat and their wine may abound,</hi> they are at a point for religion. Fewe there be whoſe <hi>Hearts are ſtabliſhed</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 13.9.</note> and which <hi>knowe</hi> Chriſts <hi>voice.</hi> from the <hi>voice of a ſtraunger</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 10.4.5.</note>: whether <hi>Baal be God,</hi> or <hi>Iehouah be God</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1. Kin. 18.21.</note> their meaning is neuer to put it to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16518:15"/> How ſhall theſe ſtand to defend Religion, who know not what that is which we call Religion. When we ſhall ſee men caring and ſtudying and taking paines to find out that which <hi>Luke</hi> calleth <hi>The Certenty</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 1.4.</note> and not to be led by coniecturall ſuppoſitions, but (as he ſpeaketh) to be <hi>fully perſwaded</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">v. 1.</note>, then there will be ſome hope, that the Lords part will encreaſe, in the meane time, while they make either the Times, or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or their owne Humour to be the meaſure of their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we may be ſure, the cauſe of God ſhall from them receiue very ſmall vpholding. The ſecond Evil, is the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardize and faint-hartednes of the moſt Profeſſours that I may folow the Phraſe of my Text; they are like to ſome vnexperienced and lately-pteſſed ſouldiers, who, while the training and muſter is neere home vpon a faire greene, where they are neither ſcanted for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, nor ſtraitened for lodging, nor in any hazard of life, march with ſome ſhew of reſolution, a man would thinke they would euen eate vp the enemy, but when they come to behould the face of warre in his true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, the battaile pitched, and a furious enemie in fight euen now inſtantly to be charged; their hearts faile them, and the ſound of the drumme is vnto them as their paſſing bell and they would giue a world to ſee the ſmoke of their country chimnies: Euen ſo, many profeſſours of Religion, while the world applaudes their forwardnes, and when the <hi>people before,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> that folow<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>crie Hoſanna</hi> vnto Chriſt, who but they? a man would thinke (that I may vſe <hi>Salomons</hi> phraſe)<note n="d" place="margin">can. 8.7</note> that <hi>much water could not quench their Loue, neither the Flouds drowne</hi> their zeale, but when it commeth to blowes, the world frownes, profit is abridged, pleaſure is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, credit and fame is a litle eclipſed, their names put out as Euill<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 6.22.</note>, then they are nipt: like an ouerforward budde with an vntimely froſt, then begin they to grow to a demurre, and in fine, either runne away in the plaine of field, or elſe (vnder a colour of diſcretion) fall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16518:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> backe into the rereward, the battell is ſharpe, and it is not good to be too forward. Thus like as in <hi>Gedeons</hi> enterpriſe<note n="f" place="margin">Iud. 7.</note>, of two and thirtie thouſand which tooke armes, when proclamation was made in the campe (the aſſault approching) <hi>who ſo is timerous let him returne,</hi> at one clap, there went away two and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; ſo of troupes of profeſſors which at the firſt entrance giue in their names, when it commeth to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the greateſt part will retire, and they wilbe but a fewe, that will ſtand vnto it to the end. Hereby you may ſee, that when we haue (as Ieremie ſaih<note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 5.</note>) <hi>runne to and fro, through our streetes,</hi> and made enquiry, we ſhall finde but few, who if they were now to end their daies, and to looke backe into their courſe paſt to ſee how they haue demeaned themſelues in this holy warfarre, are able to ſay, without an inward check, I <hi>haue fought that good fight, and now I exspect the crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, we haue all heard what <hi>Paul</hi> did, he <hi>fought that good fight:</hi> how comfortable it was that he had done it, it emboldened him to expect a <hi>Crowne of Righteouſnes:</hi> we haue ſeene our owne careleſnes, and what wilbe the iſſue if we continue it: <hi>the ſecond death</hi> is prouided for <hi>the Fearfull</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Reu. 21.8.</note>, but ſuch as <hi>ouercome, ſhall inherit all things</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">v. 7.</note>. If we deſire comfort in death and happines after death, let vs henceforth arme our ſelues for this ſpirituall fight, againſt our owne Corruption, againſt Sathans temptation, againſt Sathans inſtruments which fight againſt Religion. This is the only warre, which is the way vnto eternall <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Let God alone haue the Glory.</closer>
            <trailer>The end of the first Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16518:16"/>
            <head>The ſecond Sermon. The worth of the water of Life.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOH. 4.13.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Ieſus anſwered and ſaid vnto her, Whoſoeuer drinketh of this water, ſhall thirſt againe,</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>14.</hi>
                     </bibl> But whoſoeuer drinketh of the water, that I ſhall giue him, ſhall neuer be more a thirſt: but the water that I ſhall giue him, ſhall be in him a well of water, ſpringing vp into euerlaſting life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſtorie of Chriſts conference with the woman of Samaria, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be vnknowne vnto any, which is of any ordinarie knowledge in the Scripture: yet partly to giue light vnto my Text, partly to helpe thoſe which are not ſo carefull to ſearch the booke of God, as they ought to be, it is expedient for me to repeate it.</p>
            <p>It fell out, as our ſauiour iournyed through <hi>Samaria into Galilee,</hi> that he, (being a man in all<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> things like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, <hi>yet without ſinne</hi>) was both hungry and weary. To relieue hunger, he ſent his Diſciples into the city to make prouiſion; to eaſe his wearied limmes, he ſate him downe vpon a well ſide, in thoſe times and in thoſe Coaſts ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry famous, in reſpect of the Author thereof, whoſe name it ſtill caried, being called, <hi>Iacobs Well.</hi> He ſitting there, out commeth me, a woman of the adioyning city <hi>Sichar,</hi> to drawe water from thence, for her houſhold vſes. Chriſt, partly to refreſh his bodily thirſt, but eſpecially (as I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16518:17"/> take it) to ſatiſfie that his neuer-ceaſing deſire to doe good, made a motion to her, to affoord him ſome of the water, that he might drinke. Shee, (being as appeareth by her aunſwers ſomething a ſhrewd-tongued woman) by and by cut him vp ſhort; what, (quoth ſhee) you Iewes, be ſo fine and proud, that you ſcorne vs, the poore Inhabitants of <hi>Samaria:</hi> How is it then, that thou being a Iew, askeſt drinke of me, a forlorne and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Samaritane? Our ſauiour</hi> (to giue vs an inſtance of the accompliſhment of that auncient promiſe, that he would be<note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 65.1.</note> 
               <hi>(found of them, that ſought him not)</hi> doth neither forbeare to commune with her, nor yet (as the manner of the world is) doth frame an vntoward ſpeach to her croſſe aunſwer; but ſeeming to pity her Ignorance, and blindenes, telleth her; Alas, good woman, if thou knew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the great mercy of God toward thee, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his perſon and office which requeſteth thee, thou wouldeſt become a ſuter to him rather, and he would giue thee another manner of water then this, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the <hi>water of life.</hi> The woman aunſwereth him with a ſcoffe, well inough vnderſtanding his meaning, but yet ſhee ieſtes it out, as though ſhee knew it not: what art thou (quoth ſhee) that talkeſt of the water of life? canſt thou be better then our father <hi>Iacob</hi> who firſt founded this well? or can there be any better water, then this well affords? thou ſeemeſt therefore to me to bragge of more then thou art any way able to performe. Marke now Chriſtes aunſwer. Oh woman (ſaith he) thou art very ignorant, or very froward: I ſpeake not to thee, of any viſable water ſeruing for the bodies nouriſhment, but of a matter of farre more infinite worth, if thy heart were opened to apprehend it. I know the water of this well is excellent, and <hi>Iacob</hi> in his time, was a holy man; but behould here another fountaine, behould a greater then <hi>Iacob</hi> is here, euen the ſtaffe of the hope of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iacob.</hi> This ſtreame here, relieueth the body for a time, but cannot affoord a perpetuall filling: the water
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16518:17"/> which I haue to giue ſhall euerlaſtingly ſatiſfie the thirſt of the receiuers of it, and it ſhall be in their bowels, as a neuer-dryed fountaine, ſpringing vp to euerlaſting life. Thus haue you the courſe of the communication be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and the Samaritane thus farre. By which you may perceiue, that the maine ſcope of this Text, is, to ſhew the difference betwixt the things of this preſent life, and the things of a better life: the weakneſſe of the one, and the worth of the other. The former is ſet downe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Whoſoeuer drinketh of this water, &amp;c.</hi> the latter, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>But whoſoeuer drinketh of the water which, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the former, I know, that Chriſt expreſly and by name ſpeaketh of water onely; yet conſidering the chiefe drift of the place is, to draw men from the things which are ſeene, to the things which are not ſeen,<note place="margin">The doctrine.</note> from things temporall, to things eternall, from the things which are on earth, to the things which are aboue: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may ſafely from hence draw this doctrine: That nothing in this preſent world, is able to affoord any true ſatisfying, any filling as it were, vnto a mans ſoule. For that which Chriſt ſaid here of the water of this well, <hi>whoſoeuer drinketh thereof ſhall thirſt againe,</hi> may truly be ſaid of all things elſe whatſoeuer, which the men of this world do ayme at in their courſes, <hi>viz.</hi> they do rather encreaſe then kill the deſire, rather inflame then quench the appetite: they are all like to cold drinke taken by a man labouring of a hote Ague, which though it ſeeme to ſatisfie for the preſent, yet indeed it increaſeth the former drought, and maketh both the need and the deſire of moyſture greater then before. It were no hard thing to ſhew this to be true, by the enumeration of particulars: but my meaning is, not to inſiſt vpon this point, but only to vſe it as a preparatiue to the reſt. This is all I will ſay, (and I will therein craue no better witneſſe, then each mans owne experience:) If a man, liuing here in the world, ſhould do as <hi>Salomon</hi> did, namely, <hi>Whatſoeuer his</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eccl. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>eyes deſire, ſhould not withhold it from them, nor withdraw
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16518:18"/> his heart from any ioy:</hi> but ſhould euen ſtudie, as it were, to glut himſelfe with the things of this life, yet in the end, he ſhould find his heart like the ſea, of which the ſame Wiſe man ſaith, that though<note n="d" place="margin">Eccl. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>All the riuers go into it, yet it is not full:</hi> ſo neither ſhall his eye be ſatiſfied with ſeeing, nor his eare with hearing, nor his heart with enioying: but he ſhall be like to a man in a maze, wherein when he hath laboured long, yet at laſt, he is as farre from that which he ſought for, as he was at the beginning. And the reaſon hereof is expreſſe: the mind is immortall, but all theſe things are tranſitorie: ſo that it is vnpoſſible for the mind to be filled with earthly things, as it is for a cheſt of wood to be filled with ſpirituall things. It is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſaid, and to good purpoſe, by thoſe which reaſon from the forme of the world, and the faſhion of the hart; the world is round, and the heart three cornered. As therefore it cannot be, that a round thing ſhould fill that which is three ſquared, becauſe the corners muſt needes remaine emptie: ſo neither can the things of this world, (which <hi>Iohn</hi> diuideth into three kindes,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>The luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life,</hi> repleniſh a mans ſoule, but ſome one corner (as it were) or other thereof will remaine vnfilled. This briefe diſcourſe ſerueth to ſhew the truth of this point: let vs as briefely make vſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>I remember the ſpeach of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, cap.</hi> 55. whereby ſolemne proclamation prouoking all men to come to Chriſt, that they may enioy that ſame gratious fauour which our <hi>Sauiour</hi> maketh offer in this place, he doth notably reprooue the folly of the greateſt part of men in theſe <hi>Wordes,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iſ. 55.2.</note> 
               <hi>wherefore doe you lay out ſiluer and not for bread, and your Labour without being ſatisfied?</hi> as if he had ſaid: <hi>what folly is this, or what madneſſe is it, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth your hearts, O ye ſonnes of Men, that you doe ſo buſie your ſelues, and spend your beſt Endeauours, about ſuch things which cannot ſatisfie? think you it is a poſſible Thing to be fedde with the Wind, or will you cast your affections vpon
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16518:18"/> that which is Nothing?</hi> This is the effect of the Prophets reproofe: If he were aliue now, he would (as he well might) vſe the ſame words. There is indeede much to doe in the world at this day much travailing, much plotting, much contending, &amp; we do all beſtir our ſelues as though the Duſt of the earth were not ſufficient for euery man to take a handfull: one man buyeth and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth and<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>ioyneth Houſe to Houſe, and Field to Field,</hi> that he may be placed by himſelfe, to be a litle King in his owne Territories: another couets<note n="h" place="margin">Mic. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>fieldes, and taketh them by Violence, &amp; houſes, &amp; takes them away, &amp; ſo oppreſſeth a man &amp; his houſe, euen a man &amp; his heritage:</hi> a third, he<note n="i" place="margin">Am. 2.7. &amp; ca. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>gapeth ouer the Heades of the poore,</hi> and doth euen <hi>ſtore vp violence.</hi> In a word each man almoſt hath enlarged <hi>his Deſire as the Hell, and is as Death, &amp; cannot be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and is neuer well in his Conceipt, till he hath euen <note n="k" place="margin">Hab. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>laded himſelfe with thicke Clay:</hi> and we are all trudging like this woman with<note n="l" place="margin">v. 6.</note> our pitchers in our neckes, to ſome one well or other, and if it be neuer ſo deepe, it ſhall goe very hard, but we will get it out. But (alas) fooles that we be, when we haue done all, we doe but <hi>euen weary</hi> our ſelues<note n="m" place="margin">v. 13,</note> 
               <hi>for very vanity:</hi> when we haue drunke of this Well againe and againe, yet in the End, our deſire is as it was, rather ſtretched out to receiue more, then filled with that which it hath obtained: when we haue reached euen to the vtmoſt of our firſt deſires, we are then but like the<note n="n" place="margin">Iſ. 29.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hungry man,</hi> who <hi>dreameth, and behold he eateth,</hi> and <hi>when he awaketh his ſoule is empty: or like the thirstie man,</hi> who <hi>dreameth, and loe he is drinking, and when he awaketh behold he is faint, and his ſoule longeth:</hi> So it is but an imagination of comfort which commeth by all theſe things, and no true contentment. I beſeech you, let this ſhort and yet full diſcouery of our common folly, (who for the mpſt part, doe nothing but<note n="o" place="margin">Hoſ. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſow the wind,</hi> and if we ſo continue ſhall reape no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Corruption</hi>) make vs to ſay as <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſts hearers did, when they perceiued by his preaching they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16518:19"/> were cleane out of the way<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 3.10.</note>, <hi>what ſhall we doe then?</hi> If hitherto we haue aimed at a wrong Marke in our deſires, ſhew vs I pray you, how to reforme it: and let your hearts, I pray you ſay now to me, as <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 10.33.</note>, <hi>We are all here preſent before God, to heare all things that are commaunded thee of God:</hi> which I doe wiſh ſo much the rather, becauſe that which I am now next to ſpeake of is that which <hi>Salomon</hi> in one place calleth <note n="r" place="margin">Prov. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>Durable Riches</hi> in another<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ecc. 12.13.</note>, the <hi>End of all;</hi> which Chriſt termeth the<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 10.42.</note> 
               <hi>One needfull Thing:</hi> for which the ſoule of <hi>Dauid panted;</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſ. 42.1.</note> in compariſon whereof <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things but as <hi>Dung.</hi> Marke firſt the wordes, then ſee the order of them. <hi>But whoſoeuer drinketh of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c.</hi> The points to be in order opened in the handling of this verſe are theſe: 1. What this water is: 2. that there is both power and will in Chriſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it: 3. by what meanes he conferreth it: 4. to whom he giues it: 5. the Benefite of enioying it: 6. the meanes by which each man may know himſelfe to haue receiued it. All theſe pointes as they are needefull, ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall handling of them you ſhall finde them to ariſe directly from the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">what is meant by the water which Chriſt giueth.</note>Firſt, what is meant by the water here mentioned. It is a true ſaying, that the Scripture is the beſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it ſelfe, and one place muſt be expounded by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. We ſee the Light by the Light, and we doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the true meaning of the ſcripture by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. We can therefore haue no better expoſition vpon this place then Chriſts owne words els where, to which the Spirit of God hath annexed an explanation of the true meaning<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 7.38.39.</note>. <hi>He that beleeueth in me, as ſaith the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of his belly ſhall flow riuers of water of life. This spake hee</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn) of the Spirit which they that beleeued in him ſhould receiue;</hi> ſo that by water here, are vnderſtoode the gifts and graces of the ſpirit which the Lord is pleaſed to beſtow vpon his children.</p>
            <p>It is not inough for me to tell you thus much in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16518:19"/> Termes, but I muſt proceede a litle further, leaſt I ſhould leaue you vncertaine, in that which my cheife deſire is to reſolue you. This therefore I muſt tell you: that though it be true, that by water are here meant the gifts of the ſpirit, yet there are certaine gifts &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſpirit, which a man may haue,<note place="margin">Some gifts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpirit are common, ſome proper onely to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> and yet be a Reprobate. So that you muſt learne to put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, betwixt the common gifts of the ſpirit, and thoſe gifts which are proper onely to Gods children. The world is as it were Gods great Houſe, in which there are both ſeruants and ſonnes, the one (as Chriſt ſaith) <note n="y" place="margin">Ioh. 8.35.</note> to be caſt out, the other to abide euer. Now in a family, we know, there be ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fauours, which the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; drudges doe enioy as well as the heire: &amp; ſo ſome gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there be, which eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reprobate haue, which is meet we ſhould know, leaſt we be deceiued, and they are theſe. The firſt is,<note place="margin">The common-gifts.</note> the gift and dexterity of practizing a particular calling: For, whatſoeuer, men careleſlly and profanely doe imagine that the skill and art which they haue in any knowledge, as husbandry, marchandize, &amp;c. is from their owne induſtry, yet certaine it is, that the cunning which any man hath in any faculty whatſoeuer, is the ſole and onely gift of Gods ſpirit: and therefore the power which <hi>Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab</hi> had to worke in blue ſilke and purple and carued worke, is called, <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Exod. 31.3</note> 
               <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by the ſpirit of God.</hi> The ſecond common gift, is the gift of enlightening, whereby a man being naturally ignorant in the things of God, is enabled to conceiue the will of God reuealed in the ſcripture, yea euen the ſweeteſt points thereof, as of ſaluation and grace in Chriſt Ieſus. A third common gift, is the power of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and expounding the ſcripture for the common good &amp; behoofe of Gods Church. A fourth, is an ability to reſtraine and temper the affections, ſo that they ſhall not breake forth into outrage and notorious euils in the behauiour. A fift, is a power to heare the word with ioy, and to ſeeme to take ſome delight, and to finde ſome
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16518:20"/> ſweetnes in it. All theſe are gifts and graces of the ſpirit of God; but yet they are not thoſe graces which Chriſt meaneth by water here in this place: becauſe theſe be ſuch as may befall thoſe who notwithſtanding ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſaued. Many a reprobate is gifted with admirable skill in crafts and ſciences. <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſeemed to be a cunning workeman, yet was he no ſmall enemy to the preaching of the Goſpell. Secondly, the Apoſtle ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to make it a thing poſſible, to be <hi>once enlightened,</hi> and to<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 6.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>haue taſted of the heauenly gift,</hi> yet ſo to fall away as to be paſt all hope of being <hi>renued againe by repentance.</hi> Thirdly, at the day of Iudgement<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 7.22.</note>. <hi>Many will ſay</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>Lord, haue we not by thy name prophecied?</hi> yet it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaid to them<note n="c" place="margin">ver. 13.</note>, <hi>Depart from me.</hi> Fourthly, many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men haue power to conforme themſelues and to bridle many ſinnes, and to cary themſelues in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ciuility: ſo <hi>Abimelech</hi> the heathen<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 20.6.</note> abſtained from committing folly with <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife: and many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>among the gentiles excelled in morall vertues; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers we ſee (whom we call ciuill men) demeane them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the eies of the world vnblameably, who yet giue ſmall hope of any true conuerſion. Laſtly, Chriſt in the parable ſheweth, that many hearers for a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 13.21.</note>, <hi>but as ſoone as tribulation commeth becauſe of the word, by and by</hi> they are <hi>offended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there are beſides theſe, other ſpeciall graces of the ſpirit, which are proper onely to Gods children. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that<note n="f" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>God is the ſauiour of all men, ſpecially of thoſe that belieue:</hi> ſo it may be ſaid, he giueth graces to all, but in ſpeciall manner to elect. Chriſt is pleaſed, in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to terme the church his <hi>loue,</hi> his <hi>ſpouſe.</hi> The day of Iudgement, is the mariage day: and the time preſent, is the wooing time, in which he is as it were a ſuter to his church: and the miniſters are appointed, <hi>to prepare</hi> the church for her <hi>husband</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 11.2.</note>, <hi>and to preſent her as a pure virgin</hi> vnto <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Now he which is a ſuter to a woman, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being a man of worſhip and ability, howſoeuer, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16518:20"/> teſtifie his bounty, and to make knowne his loue to his beloued, he will beſtowe gifts vpon the ſeruants of the family, yet if he haue any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewell of worth and price, that he reſerueth for her, on whom his loue is fixed: ſo Chriſt Ieſus conferreth common fauours, euen vpon the reprobate, to make knowne his riches, and withall, for the good of his choſen, but the ſpeciall, and choiſe and ſelected graces, theſe he keepeth onely for the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his church. And theſe are the graces meant by chriſt in this place; &amp; they are in order theſe which follow</p>
            <p n="1">1. The gift of regeneration, which is that, whereby a man of a Limme of Sathan, is made a member of Chriſt; of a childe of the diuell,<note place="margin">The proper gifts.</note> is become the ſonne of God. That this is a worke of Gods <hi>ſpirit</hi> appeareth by Chriſt his words: <hi>Except a man be borne of water and of the ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore fitly is the holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>Water,</hi> becauſe as water doth moiſten that which is hard: So the holy Ghoſt doth ſupple and ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and put the ſappe of Grace into the drie and dead and rotten Heart of Man: So that where the ſpirit of God is, there the Heart is renued, the nature changed, the delight in ſinne aſſwaged, and a loue of holines, and godlines, as it were a new iuyce begunne in the ſoule. This is the firſt proper gift.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The knowledge of a mans owne Reconciliation to God by the meanes of Chriſt Ieſus. Hereof ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Apoſtle, <hi>The spirit beareth witneſſe with our spirit that we are the Children of God.</hi> It is true,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> the nature of man cannot attaine to this knowledge, <hi>But we</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the spirit which is of God. That we might know the things that are giuen to vs of God.</hi> And indeede it cannot be, but, that if God haue beene pleaſed of his goodnes to make any man or woman his Child, he will likewiſe make knowne the ſame fauour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him or her: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeing it is ſo greatly for our comfort. For as, on the one ſide it is the greateſt miſerie for a man, to be in continuall ſuſpenſe, not knowing whether his ſins are forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: ſo, what greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort can there be to a man
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16518:21"/> to be aſſured of Gods fauour toward him?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The gift of obedience: for, as a man that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in a houſe as the owner of it, ordereth it, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it, at his pleaſure: ſo the Holy Ghoſt, gouerneth all thoſe in whome he abideth<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note>: they are all ledde <hi>by the spirit,</hi> which are the Lords. The ſpirit repreſſeth all badde motions drawing vnto ſinne, ſpringing from the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our Nature, ſuggeſted by Sathan and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the beguiling entiſements, of this euill world, and withall it ſtirreth vp good deſires &amp; holy Thoughts, inclining to Pietie and godlines.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Praier: that is, a will and abilitie in ſome good meaſure, to haue recourſe vnto the Lord by Praier vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, and to poure out a Mans wants and neceſſities before him. For this is a generall and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rule, that as, naturally euery child, being pinched with want, acquainteth the Father, with his neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, building vpon his loue, and willingnes to doe him good: ſo he which is the child of God, hath alwaies this Property, to make Prayer vnto God his firſt meanes whereby to obtaine that which he doth deſire, and to be freed from that wherewith he is oppreſſed. Now that which worketh this in vs is Gods ſpirit: For ſeeing wee of our ſelues doe neither know our neceſſities, nor knowing them can tell how to bemoane them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods ſpirit is giuen to helpe our Infirmities, to aſſiſt vs in the framing of our ſuites, that ſo our prayers may be pleaſing vnto God and comfortable to our ſoules. And for this, the ſpirit of God is called the <note n="m" place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>spirit of ſupplications,</hi> becauſe it furniſheth a man, both with will and knowledge alſo to powre out his ſoule vnfeinedly to the Lord.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Comfort in diſtreſſe. For whereas the children of God are ſubiect to manifold greeuances, partly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of inward conflicts with ſinne and the terrors of their owne Conſcience, partly in reſpect of outward an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyances, the ſpirit of God is giuen vnto them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16518:21"/> them, to miniſter comfort vnto them, to vphold them, to make them able with cheerfulnes to hold out in the midſt of the greateſt extreamities whatſoeuer. For this cauſe, the ſpirit is called the<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 15.26.</note> 
               <hi>Comforter,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> 
               <hi>Oyle of gladnes,</hi> becauſe he doth refreſh and cheere the poore diſtreſſed ſoules of Gods children.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Strength. There are many things which the profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion of Chriſtianity requireth at the hands of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, which a Chriſtian of himſelfe, is not able to performe: as for example, when a man ſeeeth the hideouſnes of ſinne, yet in the midſt of this ſight to lift vp the hand of his faith, and to lay hold vpon the mercy of God in Chriſt Ieſu: when a man is tempted to ſinne, to reſiſt the Temptation; in perſecution to endure; in penurie to truſt vpon Gods Prouidence: theſe and ſuch like are beyond the Reach of Mans power: yet the ſpirit of God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Gods children able to effect them<note n="p" place="margin">Phil. 4.12.</note>, <hi>I am able to doe all Things</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>through the Helpe of Christ which ſtrengtheneth me:</hi> and the ſpirit for this cauſe is termed<note n="q" place="margin">Iſay. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>the spirit of strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the graces of the ſpirit peculiar to the elect, and ſignified by water in this place: briefly thus: 1. The gift of Regeneration to become Gods Child: 2. The gift of faith to beleeue Gods promſes: 3. The gift of obedience to doe Gods will: 4. The gift of Prayer to ſeeke Gods Preſence: 5. The gift of comfort, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Gods Trials: 6. The gift of ſtrength to hold out and continue gods ſeruant.</p>
            <p>How theſe things ſauour with you I know not, how ſweet they ought to be vnto you, I know wel. It is ſaid of Chriſt, that to the eyes of the world,<note n="r" place="margin">Iſ. 53.2.</note> he had <hi>neither forme nor beautie,</hi> there ſeemed to be nothing in him, why men ſhould deſire him: yet all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſaw his glorie, as the glorie of the onely begotten Sonne of God, full of grace and truth.</hi> So though theſe things happily do no whit affect thoſe,<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>which are after the fleſh,</hi> but do ſeeme euen vile in their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16518:22"/> eyes; yet they whoſe hearts God hath touched, to them they ſeeme exceeding precious, and I doubt not but they ſay in their hearts, as <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> did to <hi>Dauid</hi> after his returne from the battell, when <hi>Dauid</hi> bad him, and <hi>Ziba</hi> diuide the goods betwixt them, nay (ſaith he) to teſtifie his ioy for the Kings victorie,)<note n="v" place="margin">2. Sa. 19.30.</note>) <hi>Let him take all, ſeeing my Lord the King is come home in peace:</hi> ſo I ſay, all that feare God, ſay in the truth of their ſoules, comparing the baſe things of the world with theſe graces, <hi>Take all for me who will, ſo that my bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſoule may be repleniſhed with theſe ſweet graces of Gods ſpirit.</hi> Well, hoping the beſt (as in charitie it becommeth me) of you all, and that as you do prize theſe graces, this water of life, as it doth deſerue, ſo you will be glad to know the meanes of obtaining them, I come now to the next point. Which is, that Chriſt hath both power and will to beſtow them. He ſaith here,<note place="margin">Chriſt is able and willing to giue this water</note> he will giue them, it is meet therefore that we do enquire into his abilitie, whether it be in his power to make good that which he promiſeth in this place.</p>
            <p>Touching his power the Scripture is a plentifull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:<note n="w" place="margin">Iſ. 36.9.</note> 
               <hi>With thee</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid) is the well of life.</hi> He is the <note n="x" place="margin">Zach. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>fountaine opened in the houſe of Dauid for ſinne and for vncleaneneſſe. It hath pleaſed the Father, that</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Col. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>in him all fulneſſe ſhould dwell: In him are hid all the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note>: and it is ordained, that<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>of his fulnes,</hi> we ſhould receiue grace for grace. What better witnes would we of his power? His will is no leſſe then his power,<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>Come vnto me all ye that are wearie, &amp;c.</hi> He made an open Proclamation, he <hi>ſtood and cryed, ſaying</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.37.</note>, <hi>If any man thirſt, let him come to me and drinke:</hi> and he hath renued his offer,<note n="d" place="margin">Reu. 22.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that is a thirſt come, and let who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer will, take of the water of life freely:</hi> nay,<note n="e" place="margin">Iſ. 55.1. The vſe</note> 
               <hi>without ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and without money.</hi> What reaſon haue we (I pray you) but vpon his word to beleeue him?</p>
            <p>Well then, what followeth vpon this? We that are Miniſters of the Goſpell, are appointed by him that hath
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16518:22"/> ſent vs, to do as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> to point with the finger, and to ſay to you,<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 1.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Behold the Lambe of God:</hi> ſee the man that hath the treaſures of all grace, runne ye to him, that as was prophecied of old, you may <hi>with ioy draw waters out of the</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>welles of ſaluation.</hi> Take heed you forſake not him who is the<note n="h" place="margin">Iere. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>fountaine of liuing waters, to digge you pits, euen broken pits which can hold no water.</hi> Get you to Chriſt, ſeeke to him, if you wiſh to be releeued. This is the end of our preaching, this is the drift of all our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. You will ſay vnto me, (perhaps) this is a needles exhortation: you talke of going to Chriſt, but where is he? If he were preaching in our Churches, and working miracles in our ſtreets, you ſhould ſee how we would flocke about him, how much we would make of him, and how we would runne to him: here be good words, I pray God the performance be according. Hearken therfore in the feare of God: <hi>I</hi> ſay to thee as <hi>Paule</hi> ſpake in a caſe not much vnlike,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 10.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Say not in thine heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Where Chriſt, is to be found.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall aſcend into heauen, that is, to bring Chriſt from aboue, or who ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the deepe, that is, to bring Chriſt againe from the dead?</hi> There is no ſuch difficultie in the matter: for behold he is neere thee,<note n="k" place="margin">Pro. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>he ſtandeth in the toppe of the high places,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon.) Iohn</hi> ſaw him in<note n="l" place="margin">Reu. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>the midst of the golden candlestickes.</hi> He is in the middle of his Church, he dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the congregation of the faithfull:<note n="m" place="margin">Math. 18.20</note> 
               <hi>where two or three are gathered together in his name, there is he.</hi> It is no ſuch hard matter to find Chriſt,<note n="n" place="margin">Pro. 8.33.</note> 
               <hi>Watch daily at the gates</hi> of the Lords houſe, <hi>and giue attendance at the poſtes of his doores,</hi> there thou ſhalt find him. When <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> having bene lately at Ieruſalem, had (as it were) loſt him, <note n="o" place="margin">Luc. 2.45.46.</note> they went backe to the Temple, and there they found him. Go thou and do likewiſe: ſeeke him in his word, there thou ſhalt haue him: <hi>We</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of himſelfe and of his fellow Miniſters) <hi>ſtand among you in Chriſts ſteade</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note>, <hi>and God doth beſeech you through vs.</hi> Thou wilt ſay vnto me, yet againe it may be, thou art litle the nearer, thou wilt yeeld that Chriſt is the Well
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16518:23"/> of life, and that the congregation is the place where to find him, but thou wilt adde withall, as this woman did in ſcorne to Chriſt, <hi>the Well is deepe, and thou haſt nothing to draw with.</hi> Marke therefore (I pray thee) the next point, namely, the meanes how Chriſt beſtoweth theſe graces.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth this water.</note>There are three pipes or conduits, (as I may ſo call them) by which Chriſt Ieſus the fountaine of life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyeth the graces of his ſpirit into the hearts of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Firſt, the preaching of the word; ſecondly, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments: thirdly, prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>If thou wouldſt drinke of this well of liuing water, I doe eſpecially commend to thy godly care the Publique miniſtry of the word, not ſhutting out the other two, but chiefely vrging this, becauſe I know that if thou be a carefull and conſcionable hearer, the exerciſes of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and communicating cannot but be delightfull vnto thee. Obſerue this I pray thee, if thy heart be affected with theſe ſpirituall graces iſſuing out of the fountaine of grace, get thee to the word of grace, I meane, (to vſe <hi>Pauls</hi> words and to cut of ambiguity)<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> 
               <hi>the word of faith which we preach:</hi> open thy eares, that it may run downe to the refreſhing of thy heart. If thou haſt by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, a ciſterne of thy owne, and a skilfull draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that is (as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaketh)<note n="t" place="margin">Iob. 33.23.</note> 
               <hi>an interpreter,</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to <hi>giue</hi> thee thy<note n="u" place="margin">Luc. 12.42.</note> 
               <hi>portion</hi> of water in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> then <hi>I</hi> ſay to thee as <hi>Solomon</hi> doth<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>15.</note>. <hi>Drinke of the riuers out of the midſt of thine owne well:</hi> but if thou dwelleſt (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) in a <hi>barren and dry land where no water is,</hi> or haſt cauſe to ſay as the citizens of <hi>Iericho</hi> did to <hi>Eliſha</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">2. King. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>The ſituation</hi> of thy dwelling <hi>is pleſant, but the water is naught,</hi> why ſhould I for any by reſpects betray thy ſoule, and ſpare to tell thee, that which I know to be the truth? what ſhouldſt thou doe in ſuch a caſe but ſeeke it where it is, and labour els where to ſupply thine owne neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This is the meanes of Gods appointing, this is the ordinary conduit of ſaluation. The ſeeming wiſe men
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16518:23"/> of this world, hearing this courſe commended to them, as it were a liuing ſtreame flowing from the well of life Chriſt Ieſus, thinke it incredible, and imagine it to be a baſe a meanes to beget grace in a mans heart. I will tell you to whom they are very like in this caſe: to <hi>Naama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the <hi>Sirian,</hi> who trauailing to the prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by him of his leproſie, when he had word ſent him, to waſh himſelfe in <hi>Iordan</hi> ſeuen times, he was by and by in a rage, he looked for ſome greater matter.<note place="margin">2 king. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) I <hi>thought with my ſelfe, he will ſurely come out and ſtand, and call on the name of the Lord his God, and put his hand in the place &amp;c.</hi> This is a ieſt (thought he) am I come ſo farre to waſh my ſelfe in Iordan, as though there were not as good waters of <hi>Damaſcus:</hi> Euen ſo, many, thinke ſcorne of this as of too meane a meanes, and imagine it to be but an idle thing, by hearing to be ſaued. But to all ſo minded, I ſay as the ſeruants of the ſame <hi>Naaman</hi> ſaid to him <hi>Father</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>if the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had commaunded thee a great thing, wouldeſt thou not haue done it, How much rather then, when he ſaith to thee, Waſh and be cleane?</hi> So ſay <hi>I,</hi> If the Lord had impoſed ſome greater thing vpon vs, of more charge, and of more difficulty, ought we not to haue done it? How much more now, when he ſaith vnto vs, Heare and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The weaker meanes, the greater is his glory: the eaſier it is, the more is our ſhame, and the deeper will our condemnation be if we deſpiſe it. To conclude this point then: The water of life which is originally in Chriſt is deriued to vs by preaching: Learne thou then to come by the ſtreams of Preaching to the the fountaine of grace, the Lord Ieſus. And though (it may be) thou haue depended vpon it many yeares, as long as<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the lame man lay by the poole of Betheſda, and haſt not yet gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that full comfort which thou did expect, yet aſſure thy ſelfe that the good houre is comming, in which thou ſhalt find reſt and peace vnto thy ſoule. So much for this point.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16518:24"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To whome Chriſt doth giue it.</note>The next foloweth: <hi>viz.</hi> the Parties to whom Chriſt will giue this water. It is not expreſſed, but yet it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, For marke: <hi>He that drinkes of this water, ſhall neuer thirst againe,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: therefote before he receiued it he thirſted for it; So that it is plaine by the Text, that they to whome Chriſt will giue this water of life, are thoſe which thirſt after it, which long for it, which feele the want of it: and thereto agreeth the Scripture in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places: <hi>He</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſ. 55.1.</note> (ſaith the prophet) <hi>come ye to the waters:</hi> but who, <hi>Euery one that thirſteth</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 516.</note>. <hi>Bleſſed are they which thirſt for righteouſnes. If any man thirſt,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 7 37.</note> 
               <hi>let him come to me &amp; drinke.</hi> I<note n="d" place="margin">Reu. 21.6.</note> 
               <hi>will giue to him that is a thirſt of the well of the water of life freely:</hi> And<note n="e" place="margin">Reu. 21.18.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that is a thirſt, come.</hi> If there be no thirſting, there ſhall be no refreſhing; if no longing, no enioying: God will giue his graces, where they ſhalbe eſteemed, and eſteemed they cannot be, till the want thereof be knowne, and he which feeleth the want of them cannot chuſe but vnfainedly deſire them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>The vſe of this is very expedient. It teacheth vs how and in what manner we muſt be prepared to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the graces of Gods ſpirit: vntill our ſoules doe euen thirſt after Chriſt, as<note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 42.1.</note> 
               <hi>the Hart after the riuers of Water</hi> ſo that we ſeeme to our ſelues the happieſt men aliue if we might haue but one drop of Chriſts blood to refreſh vs, vntill (I ſay) it be thus with vs, Chriſt can neuer be ours, he will neuer dwell in that ſoule that hath not euen panted after him, and cried out in the anguiſh thereof as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did<note n="g" place="margin">Iſ. 38.14.</note>, O <hi>Lod it hath afflicted me, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me.</hi> And therefore it is no meruaile though there be every where ſo many emptie ſoules, becauſe there be ſo fewe thirſting ſoules; no wonder though ſo many are without grace, ſeeing there be ſo fewe that long after grace. True it is, that by nature our ſelues are deſtitute of all goodnes, neither is there ſo much as a ſhadow of grace within vs: but yet all feele not this;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16518:24"/> among other graces which we want, this is not the leaſt, that we doe not feele the want of grace. We are (the greateſt part of vs) like thoſe <hi>Laodiceans</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. we ſay we are <hi>rich, and haue need of nothing, and know not how we are wretched and miſerable and blinde and naked.</hi> This our ſuppoſed fulnes breeds in vs a lothing of Gods graces; they ſeeme vnto vs, when they are liberally offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not worth the entertaining. So that (me thinketh) I may not vnfitly compare the ſtate of Gods heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graces, in reſpect of the cold entertainment that they haue with the moſt, vnto the caſe of a poore man, which hath libertie to goe through the church to gather euery mans deuotion for his reliefe. He cometh to one, and he maketh wiſe not to heare; to another, and he biddeth him come againe another time; to a third, and he ſaith he hath no mony about him; to a fourth, and he would giue if he had wherewith to exchaunge: to a fift, and he ſaith he is a poore man himſelfe, and hath as much need to aske as he: And thus euery vnwilling minde fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an excuſe, he picketh out but a few poore pence out of a great and populous congregation. So it fareth with the graces of God offered to vs in the ordinarie Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of the word. They paſſe (as it were) from ſeate to ſeate, from pue to pue, from one end of the church vnto another, humbly ſuing and forcibly perſwading, to be entertained: But (alas) there is ſuch a generall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummednes, and frozen deadnes, poſſeſſeth the hearts of the greateſt part, that (I know not how) Grace, the more kindly it is offered, the leſſe it is eſteemed, and though the water of life doe runne (as it were) tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our ſtreetes, yet men will ſcarſely ſtoope to receiue it. I am euen woe to thinke vpon it, how men and women, that now thinke all is well inough, and doe <note n="i" place="margin">Cor. 7.1.</note> receiue <hi>the grace of God in vaine, and</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>neglect ſo great ſaluation,</hi> ſhall one day with teares of blood be ſuters for one drop of grace, and yet ſhall not be able to obtaine it. Well then if we would drinke of the water which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16518:25"/> Chriſt hath to giue vs, let vs labour to thirſt after it: you wil ſay vnto me,<note place="margin">How to be brought to thirſt for Chriſt.</note> how ſhall we come to this ſpirituall thirſt. I will ſhew you how. There be two things e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially beget thirſt: the one is Labour. I neede not prooue it, yoe know it well inough by experience: ſo then a ſpirituall labour will beget a ſpirituall thirſt. But what is this ſpirituall Labour, It is this: a trauailing vnder the waite and burthen of a mans owne ſinnes: If thou canſt once ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 38 4.</note> 
               <hi>My ſinnes are like a ſore bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> too heauie for me to beare, thou wilt quickly thirſt after the righteouſnes of Chriſt Ieſus. Another occaſion of thirſt is ſalt, you knowe that by experience alſo. Now marke what Chriſt ſaith, he telleth the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors, that in reſpect of their Miniſtry,<note n="m" place="margin">Math. 5.13.</note> they <hi>are the ſalt of the Earth.</hi> ſalt hath a kind of biting nature, ſo hath the word well applied; it is ſharpe &amp; eager, and he who is well exerciſed vnder it, and well ſchooled, by the vrging of the lawe vpon his conſcience he will ſoone thirſt after the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offered in Chriſt Ieſus The Goſpell will be glad tidings to him, and<note n="n" place="margin">Pro. 25.25.</note> 
               <hi>as cold waters to a weary ſoule.</hi> Take this courſe which I haue preſcribed thee, learne to feele the waite of ſinne, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the powerfull miniſtery of the word, and thou ſhall ſoone thirſt for the water of life.</p>
            <p>The next point is the benefit of enioying this water. <hi>He that drinketh of it ſhall neuer be more a thirſt.</hi> And the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, becauſe the <hi>water ſhalbe in him, a wel of water ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp into euerlaſting life.</hi> This is warily to be vnderſtood: for it is not ſo to be taken, as though the children of God being once ſeaſoned with grace, were glutted (as it were) and had no more deſire for the encreaſe of grace: for it is cleane otherwiſe; the more grace a man hath, the more he longeth to haue grace to be euen heaped (if it were poſſible) vpon his ſoule. But the meaning is this; that whereas this outward clement of water, which we dayly vſe, is ſoone waſted and turned to nothing, and a man that hath vſed it, is within a while as new to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16518:25"/> ſeeke, as if he neuer had had thereof, this water of life is of another nature; being once receiued, it is neuer dryed vp againe, it is like to a liuing ſpring which ſhall perpetually ſtreame, &amp; as it were bubble out vnto eternal life: it is a fountaine that can neuer be drawne dry, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ſtocke that can neuer be waſted, a ſtore which can neuer be ſpent, as a lampe fed with oyle of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality which can neuer be conſumed. We learne an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent point from hence, and it is this: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> that the graces god once beſtoweth on his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are neuer taken from them: this is Chriſts true meaning: and it is a point eaſily proued by the ſcripture.<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>The gifts and calling of God are without repentance,</hi> that is, God neuer altereth his purpoſe touching the bringing of any man into the ſtate of grace<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 13.</note>. <hi>Whom he loueth, he loueth to the end, for a moment,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iſ. 54.8.</note> 
               <hi>I hide my face from thee for a litle ſeaſon, but with euerlaſting loue</hi> I <hi>had compaſſion on thee ſaith the Lord thy redeemer.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 31.3.</note> 
               <hi>I haue loued thee with an euerlaſting loue.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Phil. 1.16.</note> I <hi>am perſwaded</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) that he that hath begun this worke in you will performe it.</hi> It is a generall rule; where God begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a good worke of grace, he goeth one alwaies to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it. <hi>I giue vnto my ſheepe eternall life, and they ſhall neuer periſh, neither ſhall any pluck them out of my hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28.</note> There is no point plainer in the ſcripture; Chriſt doth not bring vs into a good courſe, and then leaue vs to our ſelues, but he guides vs in it by his grace vnto the end; therefore he is called both<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 12.2. The vſe</note> 
               <hi>the author, and the finiſher of our faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe is two-fold: firſt, to quicken and ſtirre vp our deſires to make vs labour after theſe heauenly graces, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are the onely things of perpetuitie. All things elſe are ſubiect to vncertaintie, onely<note n="v" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>the foundation of the Lord remaineth ſure.</hi> Oh then, chuſe the<note n="*" place="margin">Luc. 10.42.</note> 
               <hi>better part which ſhall not be taken away from vs.</hi> Secondly, this is a point of infinite and vnſpeakable comfort to all Gods children. For conſider I pray you, is it not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable thing, when a man with great charge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie hath gotten a commoditie, to be aſſured of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16518:26"/> continuance, and to be freed from the feare of looſing it? what a ioy muſt it then needes be to a Chriſtian ſoule, to conſider that the Lord hauing begun, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be gracious vnto him: will neuer alter his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, that grace being once beſtowed, ſhall neuer bee withdrawne, that his ſoule hauing once bene moiſtened with the dew of heauen, ſhall neuer be wholy dryed vp againe. It is poſſible I know for the deare child of God, ſometimes to ſeeme to himſelfe and to others, emptie and barren of all goodneſſe, and theſe graces may be thought for a time, vtterly to be conſumed. So the ſap lyeth hid in the roote of the tree the whole winter, and maketh no ſhew; and in a very drie and hotte Sommer, you ſhall ſee many ſprings as it were cleane gone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any appearance of moiſture: yet in Sommer the ſap mounteth aloft into all the branches of the tree, and in a conuenient ſeaſon, the veines of the earth are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the dryed ſpring returneth to his former ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: ſo, though the children of God may ſeeme ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vtterly to be fallen backe to their former hardnes, yet (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith)<note n="x" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.9.</note> there is a certaine ſeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; there is a hidden moyſture which at laſt breakes out, and ſheweth it ſelfe in the fruites of righteouſneſſe as before. So then, if thou haſt neuer ſo little grace, (as thou thinkeſt) though it be but as yet a deſire of grace, a longing after faith, a thirſting after righteouſneſſe, yet make much of it, reioyce in it, thank God for it, take it as a pledge that the Lord hath ſome further worke to worke in thee: be ſure, that he which hath begun it, will cheriſh it, yea and that in his time he will alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſignes of hauing this water.</note>The laſt point remaineth, which is the life of all, that hath bene ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> how may I for my part know that I haue taſted of this water. Hearken a litle and I will tell thee: thou ſhalt know the certaintie of it by theſe ſignes. The firſt is, a cleare fight of thine owne ſoules eſtate. In a cleare well, a man ſhall ſee a peny in the bottome of it: ſo if a man haue the well of life in his heart, he ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16518:26"/> in it the full proportion (as it were) of his owne ſoule. And aſſure thy ſelfe of this, that the more full ſight thou haſt of thine owne imperfections, of thine owne corruptions, of the rebellions of thy heart, of the crookedneſſe of thy nature, the greater portion thou haſt of this grace. The ſecond ſigne, is the cleaneneſſe of the heart: it is the nature of the water to cleanſe and ſcoure: ſo is it the propertie of this heauenly water: no ſope, no nitre, hath that ſcouring power that it hath.<note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>The heart is wicked aboue all things:</hi> fraughted naturally with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ignorance, vnbeleefe, hardneſſe, ſecuritie, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, vntovvardneſſe to good ſeruices. Looke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hovv thy heart is cleanſed, thy ſoule purged from this filthineſſe. Thou vvilt ſay to me (perhaps) the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith,<note n="z" place="margin">Pro. 20.9.</note> 
               <hi>Who can ſay, I haue made my heart cleane:</hi> hovv ſhall I then thinke to find a cleane heart? I anſvver, cleane from all blemiſh I knovv thou ſhalt neuer find it, yet thou muſt<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 5.4</note> haue a pure heart, for elſe thou ſhalt neuer ſee God. A pure heart, is a heart purged from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of ſinne, a heart<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>cleanſed from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God:</hi> more plainely, a heart<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 13.18.</note> 
               <hi>which deſireth in all things to liue honeſtly.</hi> If thou vvouldſt therefore be ſure of a cleane heart, looke for a cleane conuerſation, ſuch a conuerſation as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note n="d" place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> vvhich <hi>becommeth the Goſpell,</hi> vvhich adorneth <hi>the doctrine of God our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in all things,</hi> vvhich maketh our enemies and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our profeſſion<note n="e" place="margin">Tit. 2.10. verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>aſhamed when they haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning vs to ſpeake euill of.</hi> The water of life doth alwayes bring forth ſuch fruite: therefore a good man is ſaid to be<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>as a tree planted by the riuers of water, that will bring forth her fruite in due ſeaſon.</hi> And it is ſaid againe,<note n="g" place="margin">Ezek. 47.9.</note> 
               <hi>that euery thing ſhall liue, whither that liuing ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> which floweth out of the Sanctuarie, <hi>commeth.</hi> Try thy ſelfe by this marke, ſee whether this water hath quenched the boyling heate of thine owne inordinate luſts, and hath begotten a new life, euen the life of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe within thee. The third ſigne, is encreaſing in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16518:27"/> grace: water which is but a ſmall ſtreame at the well head, going further waxeth broader and deeper, and partes it ſelfe into many branches: ſo theſe waters that flowed out of the Sanctuarie, were firſt<note n="h" place="margin">Ez. 47.3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>to the ancles,</hi> then to the <hi>knees,</hi> then to the loynes, then <hi>a riuer which could not be paſſed ouer.</hi> If there be a care to increaſe in grace, in knowledge, in feeling, in zeale, in obedience, the well of life is in that ſoule: if there be a reſting ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as though all were well, and we had religion i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that is a dry ſoule, the graces of Gods ſpirit are not in it. The fourth ſigne, is a care to do good to the ſoules of others: we know nothing is more free in vſe then the water. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſ. 104.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>God ſendeth out ſprings in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the valleys, to giue drinke to all the beaſts of the field.</hi> And Chriſt ſaith,<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 7.38.</note> that <hi>out of his belly,</hi> which drinketh of this water, <hi>ſhall flow riuers of water of life,</hi> by which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall be comforted. Haſt thou a deſire and a care to be helpefull to other mens ſoules? it is a ſigne, thy ſoule is watered, and ſhall be more bedewed: for<note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>he that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth ſhall haue raine:</hi> haſt thou no ſuch care, no diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be a meanes of ſaluation vnto others? thou haſt a barren heart, and a graceleſſe ſpirit. Theſe be plaine and familiar markes, and they be ſuch as will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs. The daily vſe of water, may daily mind vs of them, let vs daily trye our ſelues how it fareth with vs in theſe things. If we be trauelling by the way, and it be told vs, that by ſuch a tree, or gate, or village, we ſhall know our ſelues to be in the right courſe, we will carefully remember it, and heedfully obſerue it as we iourney. If we ſee the markes we will be glad, if we ſee them not, we will be afraid we are out, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to make enquirie. Let vs do ſo in this caſe, by theſe tokens we ſhall vnderſtand how it goeth with out ſoules, and in which way we are trauelling; let vs labour to remember them, let vs marke daily whether in our courſe and cariage we can find them. If we do,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16518:27"/> let vs bleſſe the name of God, and hold on our courſe with chearefulneſſe; if we do not, let vs be<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 11.2</note> 
               <hi>be iealous ouer our ſelues with a godly iealouſie,</hi> let vs know it is not well with vs, let vs ſpeedily enter into a new courſe, for feare of going on in the<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>broadway</hi> which leadeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And thus an end of this text.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:16518:28"/>
            <head>The third Sermon. Dauids Longing, and Dauids Loue.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 119.174.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> haue longed for thy ſaluation, and thy Law is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is truly ſaid, that this 119 Pſalme is the liuely repreſentation of a regenerate man: in regard that it ſo fully, and ſo effectually maketh knowne what ought to be the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of his ſoule, the thoughts and affections of his heart, the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and exerciſes of his life. So that the liker, by view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inward partes, a man ſhall find himſelfe to be, to <hi>Dauid</hi> in this Pſalme: the more he may aſſure himſelfe, that he is a new creature; and the further he ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue himſelfe to come ſhort of this patterne, the farther he is to thinke that he is, from newneſſe of life. Of this worthie Pſalme (the true image of a renewed ſoule) I haue choſen one almoſt of the loweſt, but not of the baſeſt branches to treate of vnto you: which, as for the generall meaning thereof, it is agreeing to the reſt of the holy and heauenly matter of the Pſalme, ſo in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,<note place="margin">The diuiſion.</note> it is an expreſſe witneſſe vnto vs of two things: firſt, <hi>Dauids</hi> longing: ſecondly, <hi>Dauids</hi> loue. His longing was for ſaluation, <hi>O Lord</hi> I <hi>haue longed for thy ſaluation:</hi> his loue was the lawe, <hi>And thy law is my delight.</hi> Of theſe two in order.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:16518:28"/>
            <p>In the former we are briefely to examine two things:<note place="margin">The firſt part.</note> firſt what is ſaluation: ſecondly what it is to long for ſaluation. By ſaluation is ment here no other thing, but that which in the Scripture is ſomtime called<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 19 29.</note> 
               <hi>life eternal,</hi> ſometimes <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>kingdome of heauen,</hi> ſometimes<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>the glory which ſhalbe ſhewed</hi> hereafter, ſometimes<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal 27.13.</note> 
               <hi>the goodnes of the Lord in the land of the liuing,</hi> ſometimes<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> ſometimes<note n="f" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance immortall and vndefiled which fadeth not,</hi> in a word, <note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> thoſe vnſpeakable, and not to be conceiued bleſſings, <hi>which God hath prepared for thoſe that loue him.</hi> This was (as we ſay) the obiect, the marke of <hi>Dauids</hi> longing. This ſaluation he calleth the Lords <hi>(thy ſaluation)</hi> becauſe as for vs, it is neither an inheritance which we are borne vnto, nor a purchaſe which by any deſert we can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, ſo it is the Lords euery way: it is he which hath<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> firſt <hi>prepared it:</hi> it is he which hath freely diſpoſed it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 11.26.1.</note> 
               <hi>God pleaſure</hi> of his owne will: it is he which<note n="k" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>reſerueth it in heauen, for</hi> thoſe, who are<note n="l" place="margin">Iud. 1.</note> 
               <hi>reſerued vnto Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Now what it is to long, we doe all well inough conceiue, either by experience in our ſelues, or by obſeruation in others, we know it to be the ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the deſire vnto the higheſt ſtraine; it affecteth the heart in that meaſure, that all delaies are euen a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry killing to the ſoule, neither can there be any content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or true ſatiſfaction, but onely in the fruition of that which is longed for. <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe deſcribeth this affection of his by very paſſionate and effectuall termes. <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule thirſteth for God, as the Heart brayeth for the riuers of water,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſ. 84.2.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule fainteth for the courts of the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 119. ver. 20.</note>. <hi>My heart breaketh for the deſire it hath:</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">ver. 131.</note> 
               <hi>I opened my mouth and panted.</hi> He was as one who needes to gape for a new ſupply of breath, ſuch was the heate and egernes of his perfult. Theſe things ſhew, that <hi>Dauids</hi> longing was no ſlight deſire, ariſing in ſome paſſion, which kinde of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire many times, is as ſoone quenched as kindled; but it was an ardent affection, ſpringing from a deede appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16518:29"/> of the good of the thing deſired, and being in a manner impatient of delaies, till the thing it ſelfe were enioyed. Adde hereto, that whereas there are in ſaluation two things; the one the poſſeſſion of it in heauen, which <hi>S. Peter</hi> calleth,<note n="q" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>the end of our faith,</hi> the other the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it here on earth, which <hi>S. Paul</hi> termeth,<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> 
               <hi>the firſt fruites of the ſpirit, Dauids</hi> longing was extended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both: for (to vſe <hi>Pauls</hi> phraſe) he did euen<note n="ſ" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſigh</hi> in himſelfe, <hi>deſiring to be clothed with that houſe which is from heauen,</hi> and he longed alſo for<note n="t" place="margin">Eph. 1.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>the earneſt of the ſpirit,</hi> to be a pledge to his ſoule of the future inheritance. Thus haue I briefely and truly opened to you the true ſenſe of <hi>Dauids longing,</hi> the firſt part of my text. Let vs now come to ſee, what this is to vs that <hi>Dauids</hi> deſire was ſo feruent for ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doctrine.</note>It doth teach vs thus much, and this is the point which I will inſiſt vpon: <hi>viz.</hi> That in the hearts of all that ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued, there is a vehement deſire, and an vnfained longing to be ſaued. I pray marke well this point, and be not ready to thinke it a ſlight obſeruation, till you haue heard it well prooued and well preſſed. Firſt of all, touching the ſenſe thereof, it muſt be vnderſtood with this caution and limitation, namely that I doe not extend it to ſuch infants and litle ones, which doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto the election of grace, but onely to ſuch as are of yeares of diſcretion, which are of power and ability to conceiue and vnderſtand, and are come to haue the vſe of theſe naturall powers of deſiring and longing which are in all. For as touching the reſt, as God hath his part in many ſuch (<note n="u" place="margin">Moth. 19.14.</note> 
               <hi>for of ſuch is the kingdome of God</hi>) ſo his manner of drawing them into the ſtate of grace, and of their apprehending it, is knowne onely to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. This is the meaning of the Doctrine. Now for proofe of it this one example of <hi>Dauid</hi> is a ſufficient ground: for, ſeeing al Gods children are guided by one ſpirit, and like the children of one family, ſprong of one father, and bred vp after one faſhion, are of one diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16518:29"/> in reſpect of ſpirituall things, it muſt needs folow that the longing after ſaluation which was in <hi>Dauid,</hi> is (though not happily in the ſame meaſure, yet for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall nau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e thereof) in all that ſhall be ſaued, and they are able in the witnes of a good conſcience to ſay as he did here, <hi>O Lord I haue longed for thy ſalvation.</hi> Yet, left ignorance in the courſe of holy Scripture, ſhould make vs to behold Dauid in this moode, like a Pellicane in the wildernes, ſuppoſing him to be alone herein, and ſo ſhould become negligent to frame our ſelues to ſo good a Paterne, let vs ſee whether the like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection be not to be found in others of gods ſaints. Begin firſt with <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull, without likenes to whoſe faith there can be no ſaluation: what ſaith Chriſt of him<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 8.56.</note>? <hi>your Father Abraham re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced to ſee my day, &amp; he ſaw it and was glad.</hi> We knowe what our Sauiour meaneth by <hi>(his Day)</hi> to wit, his comming in the fleſh for the redemption of mankind. This day of Chriſt, <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſaw a farre off,</hi> and as he reioyced to be aſſured of it, ſo we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, that it was the principall deſire of his ſoule, to be interreſſed into the ſaluation which was procured by it in due time. The more <hi>Abraham</hi> reioyced in it, the more he longed for it, and with the greater deſire he expected it, with the greater gladnes of ſpirit he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained it. Come downe a litle lower from him, to <hi>Iacob:</hi> that one voice of his vttered by him in greate vehemencie vpon his death-bed, while he was telling the future eſtate of his progenie, ſhall witnes the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Heart in this caſe<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 49.19.</note>: <hi>O Lord I haue waited for thy ſaluation.</hi> He ſaw by the ſpirit of prophecie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles and miſeries like to come vpon his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, therefore as a man weaned from outward things by this meanes, and taught to rely only vpon the Lord he crieth out, <hi>O Lord I haue waited for thy ſaluation.</hi> Was it not the longing after Chriſt, which made<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes eſteeme the rebuke of Chriſt greater riches then the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16518:30"/> of Egipt?</hi> was not <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his heart full of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and was he not euen readie to faint in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after the mercy of God, when he cried out in the Anguiſh of his ſoule,<note n="a" place="margin">Iſ. 38.14.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord it hath oppreſſed me, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me?</hi> Was not <hi>Iobs</hi> deſire earneſt, when feeling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be euen ouercome of ſorow, he braſt out into theſe words,<note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Lord ceaſe and leaue of from me, that</hi> I <hi>may take a litle comfort?</hi> In a word, let our ſauiour, teſtimonie be ſufficient for the longing of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and righteous men that liued in thoſe elder times,<note n="c" place="margin">Math. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>I ſay vnto you that many Prophets and righteous men haue deſired to ſee thoſe things which you ſee, &amp;c.</hi> If wee conſider the times of Chriſts viſible being on earth, and after, we ſhall ſee the ſpirit of God like himſelfe, and bringing forth the ſame fruites, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Gods children. Old Simeon a holy man, here is his ſtile,<note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>He waited for the conſolation of Iſrael,</hi> and he deſired life but onely to ſatisfie this longing <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an honourable counſeller, yet here was his glory,<note n="e" place="margin">Luc. 23.51.</note> 
               <hi>He waited</hi> (or longed) <hi>for the kingdome of God. Paul</hi> may ſtand inſteede of many examples: what (thinke we) did he long for, when he vttered thoſe words,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this bodie of death:</hi> adde to this, his<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> 
               <hi>ſighing in himſelfe,</hi> his<note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>deſiring to be with Christ.</hi> The Iewes that heard <hi>Peter</hi> preach and were pricked by his ſtinging ſermon, called to them,<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall wee doe?</hi> was not there lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging? The poore perplexed Iaylor which came to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> with a crie, <hi>Sirs</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 10.30.</note> 
               <hi>what must</hi> I <hi>doe to be ſaued,</hi> was not his deſire feruent? I might bring in a cloud of witneſſes, but theſe may ſuffice to ſhew the generall diſpoſition and affection of all Gods Children; All their ſoules be hungry ſoules, all their hearts be longing hearts, the maine thing affected by them is ſaluation. If you will haue a reaſon for it, it is no heard matter to yeeld a very ſufficient one. There are three things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a chriſtian: 1. By a feeling of ſinne to ſeeke Chriſt. 2. By a holy faith to finde Chriſt. 3. By newnes
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16518:30"/> of life to dwell with Chriſt. The firſt of thoſe three, is this ſame longing for ſaluation which I intreat of: and therefore, as in a ladder there is no comming to the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſteppe, but by the nethermoſt, ſo there is no dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Chriſt which is the height of happines in this life but by finding him, found he cannot be but by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; to ſeeke him and to long for him are all one: no man ſeekes him but he which longs for him, and no man longs for him, but he will care to ſeeke him. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this point therefore for granted, becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſee no reaſon why it ſhould be denied, I will apply my ſelfe to the applying of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> pray you in the feare of God obſerue it. There is nothing which concerneth a Chriſtian more,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> if either we reſpect the ſtrait charge giuen for it, or the great comfort riſing out of it, then to ſeeke to aſſure his ſoule that he is in the number of thoſe that ſhall be ſaued. What true comfort can a man take in any thing, who is vnreſolued in a matter of this conſequence? he may haue a kind of ſlight and deceitfull gladnes, but (as <hi>Iob ſaith,</hi> of the Ioy of Hipocrites)<note n="l" place="margin">Iob. 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>it is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and<note n="m" place="margin">Pro. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>when he dieth, his hope periſheth,</hi> and<note n="n" place="margin">Iob. 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>his candle ſhalbe put out with him.</hi> Well then, it being a matter of that behoofe to euery man, to make his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eſtate ſure vnto his ſoule, know this of a truth (I ſpeake it not as deſiring to deceiue, but as labouring to reſolue) that there is no more certaine courſe then this, to try thy ſelfe &amp; to examine thy ſelfe by this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy paterne, compounded of ſo many worthy examples; aſſure thy ſelfe the liker thou art to them in this Affection, the neerer art thou to life and happines, and the leſſe thou art transformed into this Image, the more of the corrupt old man abideth in thee, and if thou hold on ſo, when the day commeth in which eternall life, ſhall be ſhared out vnto thoſe for whome it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, Chriſt ſhall diſmiſſe thee with that comfortleſſe ſpeech which was ſometime vſed to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt no part nor fellowſhip in this buſines.</hi> Let it not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16518:31"/> be greiuous vnto thee, that I aske thee a fewe Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and be thou perſwaded, that it is a matter that beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thee much, well to anſwere them: what is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall deſire of thy ſoule? what is the thing which thou moſt affecteſt; what is that which thou doſt truly think thy ſelfe moſt happy if thou mighteſt once obtaine? what is it which hath moſt exerciſed thy thoughts, and for the procuring whereof thou haſt bene moſt penſiue? what is it, the diſcourſes and diſcoueries whereof, haue bene with the greateſt appetite receiued by thee? what is it, for the thinking whereon, thy ſoule hath euen languiſhed within thee? ſpeake the truth in the preſence of God who cannot be deluded: Is it the Saluation of thy ſoule? is it the forgiuenes of thy ſinnes? is it the fauour of God in Chriſt Ieſus? is it to be aſſured in thy ſoule that the Hand-writing which was againſt thee is cancelled, and that there is peace in heauen for thee, and a place prouided in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which cannot be ſhaken? is it that, when this earthly houſe of this Tabernacle ſhall be deſtroyed, thou maiſt be receiued into euerlaſting habitations? How ſaiſt thou? Are theſe things ſtrangers to thy thoughts, or doe they take vp a cheife roome in thy Affections? Are they deepely apprehended, or are they but ſlightly and curſorily entertained? Are thy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions touching theſe, ſetled, and ſuch as hold thee long or are they but like flying motions, which are as ſoone vaniſhed as perceiued? Though thy tongue, if thou ſhouldſt nowe ſpeake for thy ſelfe, happily would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, yet I am ſure that if thou talke earneſtly with thy conſcience, that will not fllatter thee. Howſoeuer it be, this I muſt tell thee, that ſuch as thy deſires are herein ſuch is thy eſtate: doſt thou long with <hi>Dauid?</hi> thou ſhalt be ſaued with <hi>Dauid.</hi> Is ſaluation (If thou wilt ſpeake the Truth) leſt in thy longing? then ſtand forth and heare thy Iudgment; thou ſhalt be called the loſt in the Kingdome of God. The longing ſoule
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16518:31"/> ſhalbe filled, the careleſſe and full gorged ſpirits ſhalbe ſent empty away. This is the true vſe of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, this be the generall vſe of this point, yet becauſe<note n="p" place="margin">Ier. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>the heart of man is deceitfull aboue all things,</hi> and there is a<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 32.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirituall Guile</hi> which cleaueth cloſe vnto vs, ſo that thou mayeſt both make me beleeue by proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thy ſelfe thinke by idle perſwaſions, that thou truly longeſt for ſaluation, when there is no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, therefore I pray thee to pardon my feare, and ſuffer me to be iealous euer with a godly iealouſie, and to tell thee, which art ſo readie vpon the firſt hearing of this point, to anſwer for thy ſelfe, to tell thee I ſay, that <hi>I</hi> do much doubt, it is not ſo well with thee as thou doſt ſuppoſe. If thou askeſt a reaſon of me, why I ſhould be ſo hard of beleefe, as not to credit thee, when thou ſayeſt and proteſteſt, that thou longeſt for ſaluation, <hi>I</hi> aunſwer thee, that I am ſuſpicious, that the ground of true longing is altogether wanting in thee, I will tell thee what that is, and ſo leaue thee to be thine owne iudge. It is this; a liuely feeling of thine owne wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe and miſerie through ſinne. This is the thing which will make a man long to be ſaued, which wil make the meſſage of the Goſpell to be glad tidings: the feeling of ſinne cannot chuſe but bring forth a deſire to haue the pardon of ſinne. And indeed, in reaſon it muſt needes be ſo. For as a man which hath offended the law, and is appointed to death, (ordinarily, except he be a man deſperate) would rather haue a pardon, then any thing in the world beſides, becauſe without it, he knowes he can haue ioy in nothing: ſo he which hath offended God, and findeth himſelfe in the rigour of Gods iuſtice, to be the child of death, cannot chuſe but more highly prize the fauour of God in the remiſſion of his ſinnes, then all the treaſures and riches vnder heauen. When men are ſecure, and without feeling of ſin, though the grace of God in Chriſt, be neuer ſo plentifully offered
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16518:32"/> vnto them, yet they eſteeme it not, it ſeemeth to them as a baſe thing, they regard it not; but if once a man feele the ſting of ſinne, then he would giue the world for one litle drop of Gods mercie. The prodigall ſonne, when he liued at home with his father, and had meate and drinke enough, and knew no want, then he was weary of his abundance, and would needes aduenture further to try a better fortune: but when he had felt the ſmart of hunger, he would haue bene in the ſtate of one of his fathers hired ſeruants,<note n="r" place="margin">Luc. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>Make me as one of thy hired ſeruants. Dauid</hi> being well humbled, would take it in good worth to be a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> 
               <hi>doore keeper in the houſe of the Lord:</hi> and the poore Canaanitiſh woman, when our Sauiour had well ſchooled her, was content euen with<note n="t" place="margin">mat. 15.27.</note> 
               <hi>Crummes of mercie.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pro. 27.7.</note> 
               <hi>The perſon that is full, deſpiſeth an hony combe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) but vnto the hungry ſoule euery bitter thing is ſweet.</hi> Though a man haue formerly bene obſtinate and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 50.17.</note> 
               <hi>hating to be reformed,</hi> hauing<note n="x" place="margin">Iſ. 48.4.</note> 
               <hi>a necke as an iron ſinew, and a brow as braſſe,</hi> yet if he be once brought to ſee himſelfe as it were at the brinke, and hell gaping to receiue him, and the eternall waight of Gods diſpleaſure, readie to ceaze vpon him, then you ſhall find him tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, mourning like <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 31.18.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord conuert me, and I ſhall be conuerted,</hi> yeelding meekely with <hi>Paule,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Act. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Lord what wilt thou that I do?</hi> running to the Miniſter like the people to <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>O pray to the Lord thy God that I dye not.</hi> And they which now count euery Sermon to be the <hi>burden of the Lord,</hi> and are readie to ſay to <hi>the Seers, See not,</hi> and to <hi>Prophets, prophecy not vnto vs,</hi> would then run about vs and hang vpon vs as they did of old vpon <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> when they ſaw the glory of Gods maieſty, <hi>talke</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>thou with vs and we will heare;</hi> they would importune vs, and call vpon vs, as the rulers of the Sinagogue did vpon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 13.15.</note> that if we haue any <hi>word of exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we would ſay on,</hi> Theſe would be the fruites of this feeling, and all ſhewes of longing are but ſhewes, which fetch not their firſt beginning from this deepe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16518:32"/> of the wofull and diſtreſſed eſtate of a mans own ſoule. So then, now thou ſeeſt, there is ſome cauſe that I ſhould be ſuſpicious of thy pretended longing. For if when I looke into thee, if when I conferre with thee, if when I obſerue thy courſe, I ſee thee to be ſuch an one as the greateſt part, a man<note n="d" place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Frozen in the dregs,</hi> one that<note n="e" place="margin">Deu. 29.19.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſest thy ſelfe in thy heart,</hi> one <hi>that knowest not how thou art poore and</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>wretched and miſerable, &amp; blind, and naked,</hi> one who ſtandeſt in no awe of Gods iuſtice, one whoſe<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 119.120.</note> 
               <hi>fleſh trembleth not for feare of God,</hi> neither art afraid of his iudgement, one that yet vnderſtandeſt not what it is to be a ſinner, and how<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 10.31.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>fearefull a thing it is to fall into the hands of the liuing God,</hi> one that<note n="i" place="margin">Mal. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest it vaine to ſerue God,</hi> and a meere folly to be ſo religious as ſome would be: in a word, one<note n="k" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.5</note> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteſt thy ſelfe with a <hi>ſhew of godlineſſe,</hi> without any po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of religion. How ſhould I ſuppoſe it poſſible for thee to long to be ſaued, when thou canſt not tell out of thine owne feeling what it is to need ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Shall I thinke he longeth to be cured, who though it may be he is ſicke, yet feeleth it not? Shall I imagine, he deſireth to be rich, who though he be in want, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth it not? Reaſon it ſelfe is cleane againſt it. I pray thee therefore learne this leſſon, which though perhaps it may now be learned, yet it will find thee worke for thy life, though thou ſhouldeſt liue yet many yeares. All Gods children long vnfainedly for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, if thou haue not the ſame affection with them, thou canſt not haue the ſame ſaluation with them: thou wilt ſay, I know, if thou be asked, O God forbid, I were a wretch if I did not long to be ſaued: I pray thee be not deceiued: A ſlight wiſh to<note n="l" place="margin">Num. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10.</note> 
               <hi>dye the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> as <hi>Balaam</hi> had, thou maiſt haue and yet no longing. It is a matter longer in comming, then thou, which fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt it not, art yet aware of. Thy heart muſt firſt be ſofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, before ſaluation can be longed for: and I tell thee, it is a hard thing to circumciſe the heart, and to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16518:33"/> make it bleed, it hath a skinne growne ouer it, which is not eaſily remoued. Therefore pray the Lord<note n="m" place="margin">Num. 20.</note> which made waters flow out of the rocke, to ſmite thy flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie heart, to<note n="n" place="margin">Eze. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>take the ſtony heart out of thy bodie,</hi> to open thy heart as he did<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>Lydiaes, to put a new spirit within thy bowels, to</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Reu. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>annoynt thine eyes with eye-ſalue,</hi> that ſo thou mayeſt ſee and feele thy owne wretchedneſſe, and mayeſt feelingly acknowledge with <hi>Paul,</hi> that in thy <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>Fleſh there dwelleth no goodneſſe,</hi> with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pſ. 38.4.</note> 
               <hi>that thine iniquities are as a waightie burden,</hi> too heauie for thee, with <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> that <hi>thou art leſſe then the leaſt of all Gods mercies,</hi> with <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Dan 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>that open ſhame belongeth to thee,</hi> with<note n="u" place="margin">Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iob,</hi> that thou canſt not <hi>anſwer him one thing of a thouſand,</hi> that ſo thou mayeſt haue, if it be poſſible, but euen a glimpſe of that wofull ſcore which the Lord hath againſt thee, againſt the day of reckoning, and a taſt of the horror of hell then, and neuer till then, wilt thou long to be ſaued; then, and neuer till then, will the mercie of God be ſweet vnto thee: when thou feeleſt the intolerable burthen of a<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 18 14.</note> 
               <hi>wounded ſpirit,</hi> thy ſoule will<note n="x" place="margin">Math. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>thirſt after righteouſneſſe,</hi> and all things will be but<note n="y" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>dung</hi> vnto thee, <hi>that thou mayeſt winne Chriſt,</hi> the ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ngs of him will make thy very h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art<note n="z" place="margin">Luc. 1.41.</note> to leap with in thee, as the greeting of <hi>Mary</hi> did the babe in the wombe of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> they will come downe vpon thy perplexed ſoule,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 72.6.</note> 
               <hi>like the raine vpon the mowne graſſe, and as the ſhowers that water the earth.</hi> So much for the firſt part, <hi>Dauids longing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond parte.</note>Now followeth the ſecond part, <hi>Dauids loue. Thy law is my delight.</hi> Many words of like effect <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth in this Pſalme, yet we may not account them any idle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, but rather repute them as teſtimonies of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of zeale, the heart of a religious man being like the fire which in the ſtrength thereof breaketh forth into many ſparcles, ſo that alſo, out of the inward abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, burſteth out into many ſpeaches. Touching the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16518:33"/> thing it ſelfe, the matter (you ſee) of <hi>Dauids</hi> loue it is the lawe. By which word he doth not here vnderſtand that part of Gods reuealed will, which with a reſpect and reference had vnto the Goſpell, is called the lawe, the vſe whereof is (as <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth) <hi>to</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>cauſe wrath, to</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>ſtop euery mouth,</hi> that all may <hi>be culpable before God;</hi> but here it is taken in a larger ſenſe, for the whole word of God, and for the entire body of the holy doctrine, which is <note n="d" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>giuen by inſpiration of God;</hi> to make vs <hi>perfect, vnto all good workes.</hi> This was that which was <hi>Dauids</hi> delight, the ioy of his heart, and gladding of his ſoule, the very quickning and enliuing of his ſpirits. And it is by the way worthy to be obſerued in <hi>Dauid,</hi> that ſtill, looke what affection he profeſſeth to carie to God himſelfe, the ſame he alſo profeſſeth to cary to his word: as he ſaith, he<note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 116.1.</note> 
               <hi>loueth God,</hi> ſo he ſaith alſo,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 116.97.</note> he <hi>loueth</hi> his lawe, <note n="g" place="margin">ver. 120.</note> as he <hi>feareth God,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">ver. 161.</note> ſo his <hi>heart ſtood in awe of the word,</hi> as he ſaid,<note n="i" place="margin">ver. 57.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord that art my portion,</hi> ſo he ſaid<note n="k" place="margin">ver. 111.</note> 
               <hi>thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies haue I taken as an heritage for euer,</hi> which is meet to be noted, both for the better illuſtration and manefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, and for the diſcouery of the idle proteſtations, which many make, who if they be dealt with, concerning the true knowledge of God and the way of ſaluation, will anſwer, what tell you me of theſe things, ſay what you can, I am ſure you can tell no more but this, that I muſt loue God aboue all things, &amp;c. And I truſt I ſhall alwaies loue God as well as you, or the beſt learned. But now here is their hipocriſie deſcried, in that they haue ſo ſmall loue vnto the <hi>word.</hi> This by the way, though not vnprofitably. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>
               </label> To come neerer to the point, the thing which we learne hence out of <hi>Dauids</hi> ioyning theſe two together, I <hi>long for ſaluation, and thy lawe is my delight,</hi> is this, that it is not inough for a man to ſay, he longes and deſires to be ſaued, vnleſſe he make conſcience to vſe the appointed meanes to bring him thereunto. It had bene but hipocriſie in <hi>Dauid,</hi> to ſay he longed for ſaluation, if his conſcience had not bene
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16518:34"/> able to witnes with him that the lawe was his <hi>delight.</hi> It is meere mockery, for a man to ſay he longeth for bread, and prayeth to God euery day to <hi>giue</hi> him his <hi>dayly bread,</hi> if he yet either walke in no calling, or els ſeeke to get by fraud and rapine, not ſtaying himſelfe at all vpon Gods prouidence. Who will imagine that a man wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for health, who either deſpiſeth or neglecteth the meanes of his recouery. God hath in his wiſedome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a lawfull meanes for euery lawfull thing: this meanes, being obediently vſed, the comfortable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the end, may be boldly looked for; the means being not obſerued, to thinke to attaine to the end, is meere preſumption. God would deliuer <hi>Noah</hi> from the floud, but <hi>Noah</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 11.7.</note> muſt be <hi>moued with reuerence,</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Arke,</hi> or els he could not haue eſcaped. He would ſaue <hi>Lot</hi> from <hi>Sodom,</hi> but yet <hi>Lot</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> muſt hye him out quickly, and not <hi>looke behinde</hi> him, till he haue recouered <hi>Zoan.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iſ. 38.21.</note> He was pleaſed to cure <hi>Hezekiah</hi> of the plague, but yet <hi>Hezekiah</hi> muſt <hi>take a lumpe of drye figs, and lay it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> his <hi>boile.</hi> He vouchſafed to preſerue <hi>Paul</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany at ſea,<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 27.31.</note> yet the marriners muſt <hi>abide in the ſhippe,</hi> els <hi>yee cannot be ſafe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> The Lord could haue done all theſe things otherwiſe, but he was not ſo pleaſed, and his power muſt not be ventured vpon, when his will, by appointing an honeſt and eaſie meanes, is apparant to the contrary. Now that Gods word is the ordinary and appointed outward meanes of ſaluation I hope we doubt it not. If it were not, why ſhould it be called as it is,<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 6.68.</note> 
               <hi>The word of life,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> 
               <hi>the word of grace,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 10.8.</note> 
               <hi>The word of Faith,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeed of Immortality, The</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Luc. 11.52.</note> 
               <hi>key of knowledge,</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Pſ. 119.105.</note> the <hi>Lanterne</hi> of Gods people,<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3.24</note> the <hi>ſchoole-maſter</hi> of man kind, the <note n="x" place="margin">Iam. 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>Glaſſe</hi> of our life,<note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 2.9.</note> the <hi>Scepter</hi> of Chriſts kingdome,<note n="z" place="margin">Iſ 11.4.</note> the <hi>Kingdome of Heauen,</hi> the<note n="a" place="margin">Math 13.</note> 
               <hi>Conuerter</hi> of <hi>the ſoule,</hi> the <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 19.7.8.</note>
               <hi>Enlightener</hi> of <hi>the Eies,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15.</note> the maker of men <hi>wiſe vnto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. I commend yow to God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> in his fare well to thoſe of Epheſus) <hi>and to the word of his grace:</hi> he puttes both together:<note n="e" place="margin">1. Th. 5.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>Quench not the ſpirit, deſpiſe not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying:</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:16518:34"/> there is the meanes:<note n="f" place="margin">2. Th. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſtandfaſt,</hi> and <hi>keepe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions:</hi> that is the way to ſtand.<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 15.20.</note> Chriſt directing his diſciples how to preſerue their owne comfort, when he was gone from them; layeth this ſpeciall charge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. <hi>Remember the word that</hi> I <hi>ſaid to yow.</hi> No word, no comfort. <hi>O</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 119.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) take not the word of truth vtterly out of my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is an excellent point,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> worthy to be taken notice of, becauſe it diſcouereth to vs the cunning and ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the diuell, which is this: In good things he ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the meanes from the End, and in euill things he ſeparateth the End from the meanes. As for example, in euill things he beareth men in hand that they may ſafely adventure to vſe the meanes of damnation, and goe the way that leadeth to Hell, and yet for all that, they ſhall not be damned. He maketh a young man beleeue that he may <hi>reioyce in his youth, and walke in the waies of his heart,</hi> and yet for all that, eſcape that which<note n="i" place="margin">Eccl. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith muſt needes come after, namely, that <hi>for all theſe things God will bring him to iudgement.</hi> And yet the Lord hath ſo ioyned theſe togither, that neither the ſubtilty of youth, nor any wit of man, nor all the diuells in hell can not ſeuer them to wit, the Pleaſures of ſinne, and the Iudgements of God. Thus the Diuell beguiled our firſt parents. God hath cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled theſe two, Eating and dying with an Adamant chaine, he which did the one, muſt needes haue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 3.4.</note> yet he brought them into this conceipt, that they might Eate, and yet not Dy. Oh the world of ſoules which Sathan at this day deceiueth with this ſubtilty. Well, as in Euill he cutteth the End from the Meanes, he telleth thee, thou maiſt runne on in ſinne, and yet be ſaued, ſo in good things he cutteth the meanes from the End; He perſwadeth men, that they may be ſaints in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though they be deuils on earth, that they may haue the L. ſaluation, yet neuer delight in the L. lawe: that they may be citizens of the newe Ieruſalem, and yet be no newe creatures, that they may for euer dwell with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16518:35"/> God, though his word doe neuer dwell with them. Hence is it, that many will profeſſe to ſeeke Gods kingdome, but care not for the righteouſneſſe of his kingdome, will cry with <hi>Balaam</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Num. 23.10.</note>, <hi>Let me die the death of the righteous,</hi> but neuer ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 119.5.</note>, <hi>Oh that my waies were directed to keepe thy ſtatutes.</hi> I beſeech you let not the Deuill cozen vs any longer, if he haue thus hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto deluded vs. Let vs not thinke to be ſaued by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes then <hi>Dauid</hi> was, his way to ſaluation was Gods lawe, if thou leaue this way, thou ſhalt neuer come to that marke. If the word of God be not ſweete vnto thee, if it be not to thee, as <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Ier, 15.16.</note> it was to him <hi>the ioy and reioycing of thy Heart,</hi> thou exerciſing thy ſoule therein, and framing thy heart and life thereto, know it for a certaintie, it is a matter of meere impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie for thee to be ſaued.<note n="o" place="margin">Eph. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>Strangers from the life of God, through Ignorance,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. Art thou a ſtranger to the word, thou art a ſtraunger to God; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen cannot be thy portion, except thou claime the word as an Heritage. That I may preſſe this point fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with the<note n="p" place="margin">Ier. 23 29.</note> 
               <hi>Hammer</hi> of Gods bleſſed word driue home the naile of this exhortation euen to the Head. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that<note n="q" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>euill men waxe worſe and worſe, deceiuing and being deceiued.</hi> Therefore leaſt we ſhould (as in deede without very great care we will) deceiue and beguile our ſelues, thinking that we doe both long to be ſaued, and alſo loue the word of ſaluation, giue me leaue to teach yow that, which the word of God hath taught me, namely how and by what ſignes it ſhall appeare, that we do indeed loue the <hi>Word,</hi> and that the <hi>Law is our delight.</hi> There is no body almoſt, but if he be asked, for ſhame he will ſay he loueth Gods word, and that he were a very wretch if he ſhould not. But come to the vndeceiuable markes and vnſeparable ſignes of this loue,<note place="margin">The markes of Loue to the word of God.</note> it will then appeare that Gods word hath but a very few friends.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſigne of loue to the word of God, is, loue to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16518:35"/> the publique Miniſtry thereof in Gods church:<note place="margin">The 1. marke</note> the reaſon is plaine. He which loueth the word vnfain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, muſt needs loue the meanes by which the word ſhall become moſt profitable vnto him. It is an idle thing for a man to ſay he loueth the word, and yet not to care to vnderſtand it, not to deſire to know it, not to make conſcience to apply it. The word of God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 13.44.</note> 
               <hi>Treaſure,</hi> of which, if it be kept together in a Hord there is no vſe. If thou feede thee, cloth thee, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to others with thy treaſure, then it is vſed as it ſhould be: take away this from it, what difference is betwixt it (ſetting aſide the opinion of a wordly man,) and a thing of nothing? If thou then doe loue the treaſure of the word, thou wilt loue the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it, the right diuiding of it, the ſharing it out by Gods ſteward to euery mans neceſſitie. Thou doſt heare <hi>Dauid</hi> here ſay <hi>the Law is his delight;</hi> in another place thou ſhalt heare him ſay<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 26.8. &amp; Pſ. 27.4.</note> that the <hi>Habitation of the Lords Houſe is his delight, and proteſting, that to dwell there and to behold the Beautie thereof is his cheife deſire.</hi> And why (thinke we) were the Tabernacles of the Lord ſo deare vnto him? was acceſſe thither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by him as an idle complement? or went he like a Time-ſeruer to eſcape lawe? or like an <hi>Athenian</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 17.21.</note> to heare <hi>newes?</hi> Or why went he? Sure his loue to the Lawe, drewe him to the place where they were, which could teach him the Lawe. It was with him, as it was with thoſe whome himſelfe ſpeaketh of, who going to the Temple had the<note n="u" place="margin">Pſ. 84.5.</note> 
               <hi>Waies</hi> of the Lord in their Heart, and as with thoſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 2.3.</note> which prouoke one another, <hi>Come let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord, he will teach vs his waies.</hi> So then, thou which ſaiſt thou loueſt Gods word, let me trie thee by this rule: when I looke vpon thy profeſſion, thou art prety and ſtrait without, let me ſee now, whether thou be alſo ſound within: thou liueſt in a place where the word of God is diligently and ſoundly taught, God hath bleſſed the Congregation of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16518:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:16518:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:16518:37"/> which thou art a member, with a wiſe ſteward,<note n="x" place="margin">Luc. 12.12.</note> who knoweth how to giue euery one his portion <hi>of meate in ſeaſon.</hi> How doſt thou like this? doth it content thee or doth it burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee? doſt thou thank for it, or will not thy froward Heart, ſuffer thee to repute it as a benefite? Is this Manna as groſſe vnto thy Taſt as Horſe-bread or <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 119.103.</note> is it more <hi>ſweete then Hony to thy Mouth?</hi> If thou take no comfort in it, if like the Gaderens,<note n="z" place="margin">Math. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> thou wouldſt account it a commodity, if Chriſt were departed thy coaſtes, thou muſt giue me leaue to tell thee, thou neither loueſt the word, nor loueſt God, no nor yet truly loueſt thy owne ſoule. A gaine, doſt thou liue in <hi>Iericho,</hi> where<note n="a" place="margin">2. Kin. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>the ſituation is pleaſant but the water naught,</hi> that is, where there are good outward commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, but the true Treaſure cannot be had, where when thou commeſt to Church thou beholdeſt one, who hath got on <hi>Elias</hi> mantle, but thou maiſt ſay to him, where is the ſpirit of <hi>Elias?</hi> who is able to ſay nothing to thee to rouze thee vp, nothing to admoniſh thee, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort thee: How doth this pleaſe thee? Art thou well inough ſatisfied herewith, doth thy Heart neuer mourne within thee to conſider this? Art thou not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of <hi>Salomons</hi> Rule,<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 29.18.</note> 
               <hi>Where there is no viſion there the people decay?</hi> or doſt thou groane vnder this heauie burden, and doth thy ſoule pant after a better bleſſing? Looke vnto it, count not thy ſelfe a Freind to the <hi>Word,</hi> a Freind to God, a Freind to thy owne ſoule, if thou art not affected with this Miſerie. This is the firſt ſigne.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſigne of loue to the word, is the priuate vſe of it<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 119.97.</note>: O <hi>how I loue thy Lawe, it is my Meditation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The 2. marke.</note> There is the Triall of his Loue. The reaſon is manifeſt; where we loue thither doth loue drawe our affections. The Rich man meditateth of gathering goods, naturall Louers of their loue, ambitious men of their preforments: ſo the man of God hauing no greater ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches nor glorie then in the word, cannot chuſe but medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16518:37"/> in the word. It is but ſmall pleaſure, ſo long as we are in a garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be delighted with the ſmell of Hearbs vnleſſe we carie of euery kinde ſome, that ſo we may haue ſome benefite of the garden when we be farre from it: So it is but a flattering Ioy, no longer to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the word then we are in the Church, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſomething muſt be gathered here, which may worke on our affections when we be gone. He which heareth, and ioyneth not this, with his hearing, is but like a man coloured in the ſunne, ſo he getteth ſome ſuperficiall knowledge, but it is ſuch as can afford him no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. And this is the cauſe why there is ſo much prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and ſo little practiſed, euen becauſe there is ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle priuate exerciſe. <hi>I</hi> know there are other priuate duties, as Prayer and conference, but I do ſpecially ſtand vpon this, becauſe this is, the moſt generall, and the moſt effectuall; All cannot read, all cannot haue opportunity to conferre, but euery man is, or ought to be, maſter of his thoughts, to apply to himſelfe that which he heareth, and to vowe the obedience of it to the Lord. This is a needefull point to be ſtood vpon, either becauſe it is not known, or it is not practiſed. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may be ſaid to be ſermon-ſicke, as there are ſome ſaid to bee ſea-ſicke. They which are ſea-ſicke, as long as they are vpon the water, are of a very feeble ſtomacke, faint, and euen (as it were) readie to die; but comming once a land, and hauing pauſed ſome litle time, they beginne to forget the trouble, and to recouer their former ſtrength: After the ſame maner many there are, who being at the ſermon, are toſſed to and fro by the power of the word, their hearts are ſicke, their conſciences melt, and they are much troubled, but when they are gone, and haue a little acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues with the Aire of the world, they forget what they heard and wherewith they were moued, and returne backe againe to their ill courſes as before. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this therefore, if thou wilt be thought to loue
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16518:38"/> the word, to beſtowe ſome priuate exerciſing of thine owne thoughts, in and about the word. If a man ſhould be ſtinted to one meale a weeke, he would haue a pined body at the weekes end: what ſhall then become of our ſoules, if we thinke it inough, that they once a weeke, be fedde with the word of God, and doe not giue them ſome other priuate refreſhing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third marke.</note>The third ſigne of loue to the word, is loue to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the word<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 14.25.</note>. <hi>If yee loue me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>keepe my commaundements:</hi> ſo if we loue the <hi>word,</hi> we cannot but make conſcience to doe that which is commaunded by the word. The reaſon is this. He which truly loueth the <hi>word,</hi> muſt needes tender the credit of it, and labour by all meanes to maintaine it. Now it is the greateſt honour to the word of God, that may be, when men which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, are ruled by it, and walke according to it<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note>. <hi>Paul</hi> commendeth to the <hi>Philippians a conuerſation</hi> which may <hi>become the Goſpell.</hi> He vrgeth the like three times in one chapter;<note n="f" place="margin">Tit. 2.5.</note> ſobriety in elder men and women, and ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and chaſtity in younger women, <hi>that the word of God be not euil ſpoken of:</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">ver. 8.</note> againe, grauity and integrity in you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men, chiefely in young miniſters, <hi>that he which with ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth may be aſhamed, hauing nothing to ſpeake euill of</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">ver. 10.</note>. Thirdly, truth in ſeruants, <hi>that they may adorne the doctrine of God our ſauiour in all things.</hi> Now the principall fruit of obedience ſtandeth in two things. The one is, the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by often and diligent examination of a mans ſelfe, and earneſt prayer vnto God, and by obſeruing the checkes of conſcience, to finde out what are his eſpeciall ſinnes, whereunto he is moſt enclined, and to crucifie them. This is,<note n="i" place="margin">Math. 5.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>to plucke out the right eye, and to cut of the right hand;</hi> To renounce thoſe ſinnes, which we thinke it were ſome outward inconuenience vnto vs to forgoe. The other thing in which obedience chiefely ſtandeth, is the making conſcience of euery ſinne, and not for by-reſpects of profit, or pleaſure, or reputation, to retaine a ſecret determination of continuing in ſome one or more
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:16518:38"/> ſpeciall euils. Sinne is ſuch a canker, that it ſpreadeth ſecretly, and there is ſuch a chaine of ſinnes, that he which pulleth one, draweth with it a great many. Grant a litle one, and a great one will follow. Wherefore as it is good wiſedome not onely to auoide the plague, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen euery ragge that may ſeeme to carry the plague, ſo it is heauenly wiſedome not only to auoide groſſe ſinnes, but all ſuch ſhewes of ſinne, as may beget other ſinnes. This marke is meet to be vrged. Firſt becauſe there be ſo many hipocrites in the church, many like the <hi>Ephrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iud. 8.1.</note> who were much offended with <hi>Gedeon,</hi> becauſe he called not them to the battell againſt <hi>Midian,</hi> they would haue had the credit of it: ſo many would haue the credit of religion, that doe not care to bring credit to religion, they would be thought to be ſome body, yet make no conſcience of their life, or els they pinch with the<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 5.</note> Lord as <hi>Ananias,</hi> and reforme<note n="m" place="margin">Mar. 6.20.</note> ſome things like <hi>Herod,</hi> but not all. Secondly, there are many profane ones, whoſe liues are a blemiſh and ſtaine vnto the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, through<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 2.24.</note> whom <hi>the name of God is blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong</hi> papiſts and enemies to the truth, as though the goſpell did ſet open a window vnto carnall licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Remember this therefore alſo, to try thy ſelfe by this ſigne, if the credit of the word be deare vnto thee, if thou profeſſing it, laboureſt to adorne it, then indeed thou loueſt it, but if thy life be a ſcandal vnto the goſpel, and a ſhame to religion, thou liuing more like to a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then then a Chriſtian, be thy profeſſion what it wilbe, thou art an enemy to the word.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſigne of loue to the word,<note place="margin">The fourth marke.</note> is hatred of all falſe religion which is contrary to the word. I<note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 119.113.</note> 
               <hi>hate vaine inuentions</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) and againe, I eſteeme<note n="p" place="margin">ver. 9.128.</note> all <hi>thy precepts moſt iuſt, and hate all falſe waies.</hi> We muſt learne to beware of a fauourable and tolerable and remitting conceipt of erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as of Popery, &amp;c. It is iuſt with God, to turne a ſlacknes of zeale againſt falſhood, into a profeſſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16518:39"/> againſt his truth: as <hi>Saul</hi> not puniſhing wicked <hi>Agag,</hi> grew after, to perſecute holy &amp; guiltleſſe <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fifth marke.</note>The laſt ſigne of our loue to the word, is to loue it when the profeſſion of it is moſt deſpiſed. This is noted as a ſpeciall fruite of <hi>Dauids</hi> loue. Examine but this one Pſalme.<note n="q" place="margin">ver. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Princes did ſit and ſpeake againſt me, but thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant did meditate in thy ſtatutes.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">ver. 51.</note> 
               <hi>The proud hath had me exceedingly in deriſion, yet haue</hi> I <hi>not declined from thy lawe.</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">ver. 61.</note> 
               <hi>The bands of the wicked haue robbed me, but</hi> I <hi>haue not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten thy law.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">ver. 69.</note> 
               <hi>The proud haue imagined a lye againſt me, but</hi> I <hi>will keepe thy precepts with my whole heart.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">ver. 110.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked haue layd a ſnare for me, but I ſwarued not from thy precepts.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">ver. 141.</note> I <hi>am ſmall and deſpiſed, yet do</hi> I <hi>not forget thy precepts.</hi> Here was loue. No iniuries could wearie him, no contempt diſcourage him, no ſlaunders daunt him, no ſubtill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies or daungers quaile him, no cunning allurements could draw him from the true worſhip of God, this was an infallible token, that vnfainedly he loued the lawe. It is a rare bleſſing, when Religion is generally hated, euen then to loue religion: when maners are euery where corrupted then to be of good conuerſation: to liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly with <hi>Noah,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 6.9.2.</note> when all <hi>fleſh had corrupted his way,</hi> to liue iuſtly with <hi>Lot,</hi> in the midſt of the filthy Sodomites, to keepe pure religion with <hi>Eliah,</hi> when none can be found that hath not bowed to <hi>Baal.</hi> Many can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with <hi>Iacobs</hi> vow,<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 28.20.</note> the Lord ſhall be their God, if he will giue them bread to eate, and cloathes to put on, but are loath to endure any hardſhip for the Goſpell.<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> being barren deſired children, but when ſhe was conceiued, and the <hi>children ſtroue together within her,</hi> then was ſhe troubled, and ſaid, <hi>Why am I thus?</hi> So there be ſome, who wiſh to be religious, but when they feele ſome burthen to the fleſh to go with it, eftſoones they are wearie. Well then, he that will aduenture his life, credit and reputation for the word, he loueth the word. Theſe be the chiefe ſignes of loue. And ſo much touching <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
